<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mnemosyn[on kyrio-]euchariston A treatise of the supper of the Lord in commemoration of his death, and the manifolde benefits thereby receiued; wherein the monstrous transubstantiated masse idole of that seven headed inchanting whore of Rome is stampt to power, to giue al the to drink [sic], which make it their only pleasure to swill themselues in the dregs thereof: and wherein also the doctrintes &amp; vses which arise from thence, are most soundly &amp; sincerely delivered. By Iohn Willovghby. Exhomologesis: a praier, or generall confession or our manifold sinnes vnto the Lord.</title>
            <author>Willoughbie, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102159</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837958</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1052:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mnemosyn[on kyrio-]euchariston A treatise of the supper of the Lord in commemoration of his death, and the manifolde benefits thereby receiued; wherein the monstrous transubstantiated masse idole of that seven headed inchanting whore of Rome is stampt to power, to giue al the to drink [sic], which make it their only pleasure to swill themselues in the dregs thereof: and wherein also the doctrintes &amp; vses which arise from thence, are most soundly &amp; sincerely delivered. By Iohn Willovghby. Exhomologesis: a praier, or generall confession or our manifold sinnes vnto the Lord.</title>
                  <author>Willoughbie, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 158 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes and are to be sold in Paules church yard at the signe of the crowne by Simon VVaterson [London],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A preparation vnto the Lords supper.</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated, with some loss of print. Title taken from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MNEMOSYN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> EVCHARISTON: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A</hi> Treatiſe on the Supper of the Lord in Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his death, and the manifolde benefits thereby receiued; wherein the monſtrous tranſubſtantiated Maſſie Idole of that ſeven-headed inchanting whore of Rome is ſtampt to powder, to giue al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to drink, which make it their only pleaſure to ſwill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the dregs thereof: and wherein alſo the doctrines &amp; vſes which ariſe from thence, are moſt ſoundly &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely delivered. By IOHN WILLOVGHBY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exhomologeſis:</hi> A praier, or generall confeſſion of our manifold ſinnes vnto the Lord.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let the words of my mouth, &amp; the meditation of my heart be alwaies acceptable in thy ſight: O Lord my ſtrength and my redeemer.</p>
               <bibl> Pſal. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plurimi quotidiè ſcriptis edificantur, qui verba non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Johan. Gerſ.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes and are to be ſold in Paules Church yard at the ſigne of the Crowne by Simon VVaterſon.</hi> 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND PVISSANT Prince, King Iames, by Gods grace King of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Scotland, France, and Ireland defendor of the Faith, &amp;c. To the moſt <hi>renowned and vertuous Ladie our gratious Soveraigne, Queene Anne his wife: both their heartes deſires in our Saviour Chriſt whilst they live and raigne vpon the earth, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes a Diademe of perfect glorie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Noble Princes, ſuch is the loue which out of my ſouls humilitie I owe vnto your <hi>High neſses,</hi> that I may not but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb facs="tcp:2309:3"/>of all binding dutifull al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance expreſſe vnto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, moved ſo to doe vpon the firſt ioyfull generall good newes of your Maieſties ſafe approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, your happie welcomming, and receiving both, (by ſo manie thouſands of your Loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,) into the Garden-plotte of <hi>Albion</hi> the citie of <hi>London,</hi> the moſt ſtately imperiall throne of your <hi>Excellencies.</hi> with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſo much as it fared not ſo well with mee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſent, to participate of their congratulating mirth, in behoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (which was a thing moſt comfortable vnto all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> harts,) of your ſacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and at this inſtant to increaſe the word for the increaſing of our
<pb facs="tcp:2309:3"/>ioy, of your Perſons: I nowe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my ranke and place, a Scholler by profeſsion, (though the meaneſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt ten thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) haue thought it a matter benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to manie of the houſhold of God, and not preiudicial (I hope) to anie which will be counted the friends of God, to offer this Glaſſe and maine point of Chriſtianity, the verie tutchſtone and ſeale it ſelfe of our profeſsion, vnto your Graces favourable Clemencies; ſo much the rather I ſay, becauſe we aſſure our ſelves that you are the Lords annointed, raiſed vp &amp; preſerved by th'almighty <hi>Jehouah</hi> to ſway the Scepter of this moſt happy Land, in having your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to manage the affaires
<pb facs="tcp:2309:4"/>thereof: as eke more ſpeciallie to reare vp and magnifie his truth, which was likely to bee thruſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the walles through the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining &amp; cankerlike fretting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignements of peſtilent wicked men. Beſides, after the ſmallenes of my talent, which the Lord in mercie hath lent me for a time to exchange vnto his glorie, I ſhall moſt humbly beſeech your <hi>High:</hi> favours to be invited by me, (the vnderling and loweſt one of all your ſubiectes,) as the choiſeſt &amp; chiefeſt gueſtes, vnto the Lords owne myſticall &amp; heavenly holy banquet. By meanes whereof o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who as yet do keepe a loofe without, by taking example from your <hi>Excellencies,</hi> (which caſteth
<pb facs="tcp:2309:4"/>forth both light and life vnto our ſelues, that are within) may bee at length allured from the hedges and high waies ſide, to drawe ſtill neerer and neerer, &amp; ſitte downe as gueſtes vvith you at the ſelfe ſame table, and ſo furniſh vp the empty roomes of Chriſt his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which remaine behinde, and doe continually waite and lie open night and day, for farther &amp; more frequent companie.</p>
            <p>Thus with all ſubmiſsion en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring to teſtifie the inward loyaltie and ſoundnes of my obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient heart, which manie others both of high place and lowe haue done before mee: I will end vvith humble ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, that it would pleaſe God
<pb facs="tcp:2309:5"/>of his mercie to be your mightie tower of defence againſt all your enemies domeſtical &amp; forraigne, that he would extend your daies &amp; renue your yeares, making you ſtronge &amp; luſtie as an Eagle, for his owne glories ſake, to both your owne ſoules health &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the good of the Church, and the honour of England: laſtly, that he would giue vnto you both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Oxon: Iulij</hi> 26. 1603.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maiesties moſt humble, and truely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted Subiect: <hi>IOHN VVILLOVGHBY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors_cited">
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:6"/>
            <head>The names of the ſpecial authors followed in this tract.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Muſculus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Zanchius.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vrſin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hemmingius.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Piſcator.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Polanus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marnixius.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mornay.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fr. Junius.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:7"/>
            <head>The ſumme of the booke following contained in theſe words: <hi>This is my body.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is no man which ſeeth not that all circumstances doe make for vs. For the example of the Paſchall Lambe, the nature of the rest of the Sacraments, their reſpect, and the perpetuall analogie, and the ende it ſelfe of the institution, namely the remembrance of Chriſt &amp; the ſhewing forth of his death, and the repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the wordes varied ſomewhat by the Evangelists, the Expoſition of Paule himſelfe, &amp; the taking, the breaking, the giving of bread and wine, &amp; the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall thereof iterated by Paule &amp; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which were wont to caſt doubts e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the leaſt matters, the vndoubted conſent, and the common &amp; moſt knowne vſe both of the Hebrew &amp; Syriak tongue, and the most beautifull agreement of all the articles of our faith, and the verie conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; nature of the true body which
<pb facs="tcp:2309:7"/>Christ had, and the iudgement of al the ſenſes which Chriſt in ſearching out the nature of a body commands vs to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vnto: beſides<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the avoiding of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite fictitiall and counterfeit miracles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the order of nature, and lastly the coniunction of minds wel-neere of all the ancient in the primitiue church, doe moſt plainely declare, that thoſe words are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither true, but yet placed in the Signe and Sacrament, and they muſt be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Sacramentally, that is, by ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is vſuall vnto all the Sacraments.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2309:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2309:8"/>
            <head> A preparation vnto the Lordes Supper; out of which moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable doctrines are offered vnto every beleeving hart, and the errors of the Maſse made odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and deteſtable even to all, which are not already forestalled &amp; wilfully blinded in the dotages thereof.</head>
            <head>The Supper, what it is.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Seale of the promiſe of the Goſpell, inſtituted by Chriſt himſelfe, wherein God doth ſeale vnto all thoſe that doe worthelie receive it, all the benefites &amp; bleſſings, which his own Sonne hath merited for vs through his obedience, by giving vp his body vnto death, and by powering forth and ſhedding of his bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In generall, note from hence Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The word or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of God the inſtitutour heereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The externall Signe:</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2309:9"/>
            <p n="3">3. The thing promiſed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Faith anſwering thereto, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the promiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Inſtitution, where taught:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Math.</hi> 26. cap. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the puritie wherof, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule inſtructeth the Corinthians: viz. 1. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: 11. cap. verſe 23.24. as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For I haue receiued of the Lord that, which I alſo haue delivered vnto you, to vvitte, that the Lord Ieſus in the night that he was betrayed tooke bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And when he had given thankes, hee brake it, and ſaid: Take, eate: this is my body which is broken for you: This doe yee in remembrance of mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>After the ſame manner alſo he tooke the cup, when he had ſupped ſaying, This Cup is the new teſtament in my blood: this doe as oft as yee drink it, in remembrance of mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For as often as yee ſhall eate this bread and drinke this Cup, yee ſhevve the Lords
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2309:9"/>death till hee come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherefore let a man therefore exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note heere, how S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule ſaith: <hi>For I haue receaued of the Lord,</hi> which I alſo haue delivered vnto you, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherby it appeareth, that the forme of celebrating the Lordes Supper muſt be taken from the inſtitution thereof, whoſe partes are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, on the behalfe of the Paſtour, to ſhewe forth the death of the Lord by preaching his word: to ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctifie the bread &amp; wine, the name of God being called on, and his inſtitution being explicated togither with praiers; &amp; then to deliver the bread broken to be eaten: &amp; the cup receaved to bee drunken with giving of thankes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly on the behalfe of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to trie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelvs, that is, to ſearch our aſwell their knowledge, as faith &amp; repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to ſhew forth the Lordes death, that is, with a true faith, to yeeld their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent vnto Gods word &amp; inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2309:10"/>at length to eate the bread receaved fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of the Miniſter, and to drinke the vvine vvith giving of thankes vnto the Lord. This was the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule &amp; the Apoſtles: which word, the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> wreſt mightely, to bolſter vp their <hi>Maſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt Inſtitution by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe fullie ſett downe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Math</hi> 26. <hi>cap</hi> 26. <hi>verſ. And as they did eate, Ieſus tooke the bread: and when he had give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> * thanks, he brake it, &amp; gaue it to the diſciples, &amp; ſaid: Take, eat. This is my body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo he tooke the Cup, &amp; when he had * given thankes, he gaue it them, ſaying, Drinke yee all of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For this is my bloud of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is ſhedde for many, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſay vnto you, that I will not drinke from henceforth of this fruit of the Vine vntill that day, when I ſhal drinke it new with you in my fathers kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2309:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And when they had ſonge a Pſalme, they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out into the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Oliues &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>* And when hee had given thankes; [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] in ſteed wherof S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Mark. vſeth
[<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] which a little after hee expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth alſo by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>gratias egi ſſet,</hi> that is, had given thanks, according to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Mathews wordes.</p>
            <p>Therfore to bleſſe [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] is not heere taken for to conſecrate with a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gicall murmuring, by vertue of wordes: yet are the bread and wine chaunged, though not in nature, but in <hi>quality.</hi> For they are made Symbols of the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt, not by their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor yet by force of wordes, but by the <hi>inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt, which ought to be rehearſed and opened: that faith may haue what to embrace, both in the word, &amp; in the Elements. <hi>Muſcu.</hi> Loc. <hi>com.</hi> 397.</p>
            <p>Now when S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Auſten ſaith; <hi>Acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat verbum adelementum, &amp; fiat ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum,</hi> that is, Let the word be added
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2309:11"/>to the Element, &amp; it ſhalbe a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p>Hee doth not vnderſtand by it, the word rehearſed over the Signes to be a certaine Conſecration of the Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as the Papiſts doe cogge with their five wordes of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration, barely though <hi>raptiſsimè,</hi> that is, dromedarily as one may ſay, or as t'is commonly ſaid, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtoppe &amp; turch of breath, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced: viz. <hi>Hoc est enim corpus meum,</hi> that is, For this is my body, (and yet I ſpare to tel, how they foiſt in <hi>[enim]</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie, as it were at the bynne doore to make vp their <hi>quinarie</hi> number:) but Auſten vnderſtandeth therby the word of God, who doth, inſtitute, promiſe, &amp; require faith anſwerable to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. And ſo indeede this word when it commeth once vnto the Element, it is forthwith, of an Element, become now a Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Inſtitution likewiſe out of Saint Marke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mark.</hi> 14, 22. <hi>And as they did eate,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2309:11"/>Ieſus tooke the bread, and vvhen hee had given thankes [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,] he brake it, &amp; gaue it to them, and ſaide, Take, eate, this is my bodie. Alſo he tooke the Cuppe, and when he had given thankes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] he gaue it to them: &amp; they all dranke of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And hee ſaide vnto them, This is my bloud of the new Teſtament, which is ſhed for many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verely I ſay vnto you, I vvill drinke no more of the fruite of the Vine, vntill that day that I drinke it new in the kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And vvhen they had ſung a Pſalme, they went out to the mount of Oliues, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Inſtitution according to Saint Luke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>verſ. And hee tooke bread, and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and gaue to them, ſaying, This is my bodie, which is given for you: doe this in remembrance of mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe alſo after ſupper he tooke the cup, ſaying, This * Cup is the new Teſt. in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2309:12"/>my bloud, which is ſhed for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.* that is, <hi>This cup <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in my bloud, which is ſhed for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where a double figure called <hi>meto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymia</hi> is to bee obſerved. For firſt, the continent or the thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining, is put for the thing conteined therein. As the <hi>Cup</hi> is put from the <hi>vvine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly the wine is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>foedus,</hi> that is, the Covenant or Teſtament: whereas it is but only a Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole and token of the Covenant, or of that thing rather, namely the bloud of our Saviour, by which the Teſtament is confirmed. And albeit it is a marke, ſigne, or token, yet is it true &amp; nothing vaine nor idle, &amp; muſt be diſtinguiſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that very thing, which is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by it.</p>
            <p>VVherefore by the Papiſtes leaue, (yea though they tugge and toile out their very harts about this point,) ſuch ſpeeches as theſe, viz. when Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2309:12"/>is called the Covenant: <note place="margin">Gen 17.10. Acts. 7.8.</note> when the Paſchall Lambe is called the Paſſover: that Baptiſme is the Laver of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: that Baptiſme doth ſave vs: that ſprinkeling of water is the ſprinkeling of the blood of Chriſt: Laſtly, that this <hi>Cup</hi> is the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp;c. all theſe I ſay, are metaphoricallie and figuratively to be vnderſtood. Now I pray, what ſenſe haue they that theſe wordes, <hi>This is my body</hi> (I leaue out <hi>[enim]</hi> for, becauſe both <hi>Mathew, Marke, and Luke</hi> doe leaue it out) ſhould not bee figuratiuely, ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, &amp; ſpiritually vnderſtood alſo?</p>
            <p>But by this even the ſimpleſt may ſoone perceave, how they doe nothing but dodge herein, and moſt vilely plaie the patchpannels. Yea but ſome vvill ſay; if ſo that the Sacramentes bee but ſignes and repreſentations: what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie lieth in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; ſeeing the word of God it ſelfe doth teach vs as much, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvithout the other, were ſufficient alone for vs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I anſwere that the neceſſity of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2309:13"/>the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpon this grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that is to ſay, on the ordinance of God, who will not bee called to accompte of vs for any thing that he doth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I anſwere, that the word indeede of God is all-ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by it ſelfe, had not wee bin inſufficient by reaſon of our dulnes to beleeue the ſame. And for this cauſe hee ordained the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to helpe our weakenes and dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartednes to believe any thing, vnleſſe we do with <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Thomas</hi> both ſee &amp; feele him firſt, (<hi>Iob.</hi> 20.13.) though not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally as he did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, in his fleſh and bodely preſence: but Sacramental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; repreſentorilie, that is, by Signes. And therfore we are moſt highly bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto God for the ſame, ſeeing he doth debaſe himſelfe ſo farre by theſe terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial creatures of bread &amp; wine, as ther by to apply and make himſelfe familiar to our feeble, to our ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, &amp; more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weake, yea childiſh capacitie, reach, &amp; vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Heere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are to note that three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2309:13"/>difference betwixt the word &amp; the Sacraments, in the order of confirming faith. viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The word is offered &amp; preached generally vnto all: but the Sacraments are ſingularly miniſtred to every of the faithfull.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The word is offered in preaching to the eare onely: but the Sacramentes are preſented to all the ſenſes: that ſo we may be every way ſenſiblie affected, &amp; aſſured of the goodnes, favour, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of our God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God by his word hath revealed, expreſſed, &amp; ſet downe his will vnto vs: by the Signe or Sacrament he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the ſame vnto vs. To the end, that that thing which the mind did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue out of the word, might after a ſort through the Signe, be preſented to the ſenſes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now forſomuch as our Adverſaries the Papiſts do ſtill ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle about moone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhining in the water by ſtanding ſo ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vppon the groſſe and literall ſenſe of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2309:14"/>theſe wordes; <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> that is, <hi>this is my body:</hi> (that neither they may be their owne carvers, nor we wax olde in our opinion without reaſon: reaſon (I ſay) ſuch, as they never will haue the like, vnleſſe they haue the ſame) I will oppoſe againſt that groſſe taking of the wordes, fower eſpeciall thinges to anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate &amp; infringe the ſame. viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The iudgment &amp; verdite of the learneder &amp; ſounder ſort, touching the true meaning of the wordes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The auctoritie of the Scripture, the beſt interpreters thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reaſons, with the contrarie Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, if that none of theſe, the leaſt whereof is ſufficient, can ſatisfie ſuch vnreaſonable and flint-harted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, that do moſt obſtinately put away the true and ſincere knowledge of theſe myſteries: I muſt be driven to diſcover to their ſhame, had they any, the moſt impure &amp; irreligious doctrine, vvhich they <hi>mordicùs,</hi> tooth &amp; naile defende, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2309:14"/>their <hi>Maſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt of the Firſt, that is, the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The bread taken and given to his Diſciples, he made that his body, ſaying <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> that is, <hi>a figure of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</hi> Tertullian lib. 4. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Marcionem.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After ſuch a maner he ſaith, that the bread &amp; wine are the fleſh &amp; bloud of Chriſt; as that, both the thinges ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fying, and the things ſignified, are iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or eſteemed by the ſame words. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian de Chriſm.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> did not doubt to ſay. <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> when he gaue a Signe of his bodie. <hi>August.</hi> contra <hi>Adamant.</hi> chap. 12. Againe <hi>Cyprian,</hi> he calleth it, <hi>panem ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> that is, <hi>hallowed bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The bread vpon the Alter, onely is a Signe, as Baptiſme is: and it proffit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing, vnleſſe the bread be nowe eaten within. <hi>Lut.</hi> in <hi>Serm ſuper Iohan.</hi> 6. Anno 1523.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2309:15"/>
            <p n="5">5. The Latine Church ſpeaketh; <hi>Nulla rei fit ſciſſura, ſigni tantum fit fractura, qua nec status, nec ſtatura ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiminuitur:</hi> that is, no re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting is made of the thing; onely there is a breaking of the <hi>ſigne;</hi> whereby neither the ſtate not ſtature of the thinge ſignified is dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p>And they hold this to bee the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Sacrament: <hi>That it is a Signe of an holie thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The deſtroying or taking avvaie the <hi>Proprieties,</hi> is a denying of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Theodoret. Dial.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The natural &amp; eſſential Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie beeing cutte of, the verie whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo it ſelfe is overthrowen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. For a nature cannot be found out anie way, but by the <hi>eſſentiall</hi> Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that doth deſigne and note out the ſame. <hi>Vigilius</hi> in <hi>Epist. Synod. adverſus Monothel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that denieth the Proprieties, denieth the nature. <hi>Luth.</hi> in <hi>lib. Concil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then the bodie of Chriſt is not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2309:15"/>and circumſcribed, it cannot bee a bodie. For take away the eſſentiall <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunct,</hi> and take away the <hi>Subiect</hi> alſo: &amp; once put the Adiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ct, &amp; forthwith adde the Subiect toe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vbiquitie</hi> therefore is not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated vnto the body: becauſe it is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of the divine Nature.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Do thou not (ſaith Auſten) doubt that the man Chriſt Ieſus is there now, from whence hee ſhall come; and print it firmelie in thine heart, &amp; keepe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie the Chriſtian confeſſion: becauſe he hath riſen from the deade, he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp into heaven, hee ſitteth at the right hand of the Father, neither ſhal he come elſe-where, then from thence to iudge the living and the deade. And he ſhall ſo come, the evangelicall voice (<hi>Act.</hi> 1.) bearing witnes heereto, as he was ſeene to goe into heaven, that is, in the ſame forme &amp; ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his fleſh: to which fleſh he gave immortality in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, but yet tooke not away the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. According to this forme he is not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2309:16"/>to bee thought to bee ſpredde every where: For we muſt beware, that we do not ſo maintaine the <hi>divinitie</hi> of man, that wee ſhould take away the truth of his bodie. Beſides it fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oweth not, that that which is in God, ſhould bee everie where ſo, as God. For the ſcripture ſaith moſt true thinges to vs, that wee live in him, move, and haue our being: yet are wee not everie where as he is. But that man is otherwiſe in God, becauſe God is alſo otherwiſe in that man, after a certaine proper and ſingular manner. For one perſon is God and man, &amp; both is one Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Every where</hi> by that that he is God: but (in Coelo) in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by that that he is man, <hi>August</hi> in <hi>Epiſt. ad Dardanum. Althi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dicit Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum premi dentibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, all this contention (ſaith <hi>Mulculus</hi>) ſtandeth on the right ſenſe of the wordes of Chriſt, viz. <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> where the true meaning of them is held, there thoſe arguments do make nothing at all to the purpoſe, by which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2309:16"/>they labour in laying on <hi>Hampton</hi> load of ſophiſmes &amp; fooleries, to proue that the body of Chriſt can be in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at one time, yea <hi>vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> every where.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Sophiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Vbiquitaries</hi> when they woulde proue that the body of Chriſt is in the <hi>bread,</hi> they haue nothing poore ſouls to bring but the literal words of Chriſt, be cauſe he hath ſaid, <hi>This is my body.</hi> But in the meane time, <hi>petunt principium,</hi> that is, they begge of vs this favour to grant the whole matter that is in controverſie betwixt vs. For who ſeeth not that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe wordes of Chriſt lyeth the whole queſtion, how or after what ſorte they are to be vnderſtood? Therfore the proofe of this point cannot be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. For the approbation of the true ſenſe is not to be drawne out of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wordes themſelues, whoſe meaning we doe explicate and ſeeke for: but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which goeth before &amp; that which followeth after, or els, from other like places, that ſo the <hi>Analogie</hi> of faith
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2309:17"/>may be obſerued.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Sophiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, will ye heare an other acute reaſon of theirs; <hi>acute</hi> did I ſay? one may terme it ſo, aſwel as ſome do <hi>mons à mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendo,</hi> that is, <hi>fine cute &amp; cote.</hi> the body of Chriſt, ſay they, is every where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the proprieties of the diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are communicated to it. But wee finde here <hi>petitionem principij,</hi> that is, a begging of the argument: becauſe the argument is as vncertaine &amp; doubtful, as the thing it ſelfe, which is had in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. They muſt firſt proue, &amp; not as <hi>mendicant</hi> Friars begge, that it be free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly granted to them.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But one argument now againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; <hi>viz.</hi> Whoſoeuer do take away the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties of the body of Chriſt, they doe take away the bodie it ſelfe: They who ſay that the bodye of Chriſt is euery where, doe take away the proprieties of the bodie of Chriſt: therefore whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſay that the bodie of Chriſt is every
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2309:17"/>where, they take awaie the body it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Here the <hi>Vbiquitarians</hi> deny the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: but tell them of anſwering the argument; <hi>&amp; ſurdo narras fabulam,</hi> that is, it doth pleaſe them ſo well, as though you had broken both their ſhinns with a crab-tree cudgel.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bread is changed into the bodie of Chriſt, either ſubſtantially or ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally: but <hi>not ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tially;</hi> for Chriſt, according to <hi>Theodoret,</hi> hath honoured the viſible Symbols by the names of his bodie and blood, not changing the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> but adding <hi>grace</hi> vnto the <hi>nature.</hi> Therefore it is changed only <hi>ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally,</hi> that is, it is made and turned out of common bread into a Sacrament of his bodie.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bodie is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>de pane,</hi> of the bread, either properly or tropically: non <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly;</hi> becauſe ſo al might be ſaid of the bread properlie and truelie, whatſoeuer are ſaid of the bodie, (according to that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2309:18"/>axiome; <hi>Quicquid dicitur de praedicate, dicitur etiam de ſubiecto:</hi>) which abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie deſerues an hiſſing. Therefore it is of neceſſity ſpoken of the bread <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, tropically.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poiſon cannot bee mingled with the natural bodie &amp; blood of Chriſt: but it may with the <hi>Eucharisticall</hi> bread and wine: as experience hath taught. For a certaine Monke of the <hi>Iacobin</hi> order named <hi>Bernhard de monte Politiano de Doncastro,</hi> gaue vnto the Emperour <hi>Henry.</hi> 7. an intoxicated or poiſoned Hoſt, which hauing receiued he died. Therfore the Euchariſtical bread is not made the natural bodie, and the wine is not likewiſe the natural blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This particle <hi>hoc</hi> (in the words of the Supper) which ſignifieth <hi>this;</hi> either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrateth bread: or the only accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of bread: or els the body it ſelf of Chriſt: or laſtly, (as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>Q.</hi> 78. <hi>Artic.</hi> 5.) ſome wandring and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinat
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2309:18"/>kinde of ſubſtance. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe, there was nothing, of which Chriſt, touching his body, might bee ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then this particle doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate <hi>ſubstantiam vagam,</hi> that is, a wandering or roaming ſubſtance: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, it was a determinate &amp; ſetled ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, (not a rouing ſubſtaunce) euen that which Chriſt held in his handes, which he brake; and which he gaue to his Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next, it doth not demonſtrate the bodie it ſelfe of Chriſt, neither viſible nor inviſible. For the viſible body Chriſt himſelfe had on, but hee gaue vnto his Diſciples, (after hee had broken it,) a plaine, evident, and demonſtrate thing. An <hi>Inviſible</hi> or <hi>Vbiquitarie bodie</hi> in the Supper Chriſt had none: yea &amp; the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts too doe confeſſe, that the body of Chriſt is not yet preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnder the forme of bread, when the Prieſt doth begin to pronounce this Particle [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>this,</hi> but then it is preſent at laſt caſt, as they ſay,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2309:19"/>euen after the chaunge is made: nowe they ſay that the immutation of breade into the body of Chriſt is made, in the very laſt gaſpe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherin the ſyllable <hi>[VM]</hi> is pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in theſe fine words; <hi>Hoc eſt</hi> (yet the change is not,) <hi>enim</hi> (nor yet) <hi>Corpus</hi> (nor yet) <hi>me-</hi> (now tis neere,) <hi>um</hi> here tis, Lo now he hath ſtroken it dead, now in deed hee hath kild the cow, and neuer before, till this ſyllable <hi>[VM]</hi> flue mee out of his chaps.</p>
            <p>Hence you may take a ſhort ſurview of Popery in graine, that is, in his right ſtampe, couler, and cue, as men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſaie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly &amp; laſtly, this particle <hi>(hoc) this,</hi> doth not demonſtrate the ſhew on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or accidents of bread, aſwel becauſe Chriſt held not in his hand neither did he breake bare <hi>accidents,</hi> but the verie materiated thing it ſelfe clad and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded about with accidentes: as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was falſe, that the ſhew or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of bread ſhould be the body
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2309:19"/>of Chriſt. For this were to make a body of the aire, nay marry it is not ſo wel by a great deal; becauſe that the <hi>aire</hi> though it be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a moſt moiſt &amp; fluid body, yet it is a body: but accidents are immateriall things &amp; are no <hi>ſubiect</hi> of themſelues, but they doe <hi>inhaerere ſubiecto,</hi> that is, they are faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſome <hi>Subiect,</hi> which muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and beare them vp.</p>
            <p>It is a common ſaying that beggers repeate their <hi>Pater noster</hi> ſo oft, till at length they cleane forget it ſo the fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous maſſing wittals doe beat about the buſh of Sophiſtrie and quirkes ſo long till at laſt they leeſe the bird it ſelfe, that is, they forget the maine groundes and rules of <hi>Logike.</hi> Wherfore to conclude; this Particle <hi>(Hoc)</hi> doth demonſtrat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, then the bread alone: neither doe the words of Chriſt; <hi>this is my bodie</hi> ſound any other thing, then <hi>Hic panis,</hi> that is, <hi>this bread is my bodie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice for the firſt: the two other middle motiues, (againſt that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2309:20"/>groſſe interpretation of the words, <hi>this is my body,</hi>) namely the authority of the Scriptures, &amp; the reaſons with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary abſurdities, ſhalbe ſet downe (as occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offereth) in the particular hand ling and diſcuſſing of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſpace you haue heard the definition and nature of the Lordes Supper: you haue heard howe many things do generally belong thereto. you haue had and heard the ſweete and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monical inſtitution out of the three for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Evangeliſts with ſome notes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; according to the truth whereof S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule ſchooleth the Corinthians, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth the corruptions which they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in celebrating the Supper, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them home againe vnto the firſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and inſtitutour thereof Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: you haue likewiſe receiued the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of graue and renowned learned men for the right vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of theſe words; <hi>This is my body:</hi> I haue given you a little taſte of their cunning ſhiftes and falſe arguing: that as men do vſually ſee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2309:20"/>day through a litle hole, ſo you alſo may conceiue and gather an huge maſſe of cogging, deceipt, and iugling with faſt and looſe, as it were, by the glimmering ſhine of two or three ſophiſmes and fallacies of theirs.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I haue oppoſed there againſt ſome few obiections of ours, for a bone vnto them to gnaw vpon, that ſo they may not ſcape ſcot-free away, but may haue an <hi>Oliver</hi> for a <hi>Rowland,</hi> that is, as good, nay better, then they bring.</p>
            <p>Q. Now let vs enter into the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities of this Sacrament: Howe many things are ſpecially to be ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerved in the Supper of the Lord?</p>
            <p>A. Three thinges; as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What it is in his nature and partes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What the Analogie and what the coniunction is of the Signe with the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What the meditation hereof is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his nature, it hath already bin defined: tell now what
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2309:21"/>are the <hi>parts</hi> of the Supper?</p>
            <p>A. Two, as;
<list>
                  <item>1. The outward ſigne:</item>
                  <item>2. The indward holy thing.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the outward <hi>Signe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Bread and Wine, (annexed to the preaching of the Goſpell:) which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved by the mouth.</p>
            <p>Q. Sett downe an evident place that the preaching of the word is to be ioyned with the adminiſtration of the Supper.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>Act. Apoſt.</hi> 20. ca. 7. verſ. And the firſt day of the weeke, (which is called the Lords day <hi>Apocal.</hi> 1. 10. &amp; 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.) the Diſciples being come togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>breake bread, Paule</hi> preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ready to depart on the morrow, &amp; continued preaching vnto midnight.</p>
            <p>Q. What is the inward holie thing?</p>
            <p>A. The body, &amp; blood of Chriſt: which muſt be receaued by faith, the ſpirituall mouth of our Soules: according to this rule; <hi>omnis promiſsio fide accipitur,</hi> that is, <hi>everie promiſe muſt bee receaved by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2309:21"/>
            <p>Q. Whie were two Signes inſtituted?</p>
            <p>A. The Lord did that to helpe our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, ſignifying that he is aſwell the drinke as the meate of our ſoule, to the end wee might bee content to ſeeke our nouriſhment fully &amp; wholly in him, and no where elſe.</p>
            <p>Q. Doth the Cuppe belong indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently to all?</p>
            <p>A. Yea, and that by expreſſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of our Saviour himſelfe: contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to which, we may in no wiſe preſume to doe. For it is written <hi>Math.</hi> 26. <hi>chap. v.</hi> 27. <hi>Bibite exeo omnes,</hi> that is, <hi>drinke yee all of it.</hi> Item 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>ca.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> Yet for al this, the Papiſts forſooth are ſuch braue Marchants in chopping &amp; chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging what they liſt, that they come with a countermaund againſt this, namelie that the Prieſts lips alone muſt kiſſe the chalice: as for Lay-men, they may goe with drie lippes home.</p>
            <p>Againe, becauſe they will not ſeeme in each degree to countervaile their holy Father the Pope, for whom it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2309:22"/>&amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d if he ſay no more but; <hi>Sic vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ſic iubeo, ſtat pro ratione volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tas:</hi> they haue beaten their braines for to ſearch out many prety reaſons, why the laytie ought not to participate of the wine: which one of their ſide committeth to writing, whereof theſe following are a few. viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The lay People, ſay they, do eate of the body of Chriſt, but the body hath blood alſo in it: therefore it is ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for them to haue the Cuppe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wine, ſay they, is hard to bee come by in many places, and yet when they haue it, all cannot drinke or well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with it: and therevppon partlie to ſaue charge, and partely to end ſtrife, they haue taken a good eaſie methode; that none ſhall drinke it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a daungerous thinge for the <hi>Laitie</hi> to haue the cup, becauſe of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for what can one tell, what deſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his fellow communica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts may haue. Wherevpon in ſo much as Chriſt was not wiſe enough to foreſee this deepe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2309:22"/>conceipte, they will like ſubtill whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons prevent one miſchiefe and broch a worſe that is, the overthrow of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Inſtitution it ſelfe, which is a thinge moſt vile and horrible.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Indecorum eſt propter barbas,</hi> that is, It is an vnſeemely matter for the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to communicate in the wine, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their beards: which being ſo thick and buſhie, would bee an occaſion that the bloud might be waſted, by ſticking thervpon. Oh moſt block-headed groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>To theſe adde the reſt, as; <hi>Periculum in effuſione,</hi> that is, it is dangerous in the powering forth, leſt it ſhould be ſhedd: <hi>In deportatione de loco ad locum,</hi> that is, It is danger likewiſe in the cariage of it from place to place; <hi>In vaſorum ſordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datione,</hi> that is, in the foulnes of the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which ſhould be conſecrated, and not ſo commonly handled by the Laitie and clouted ſort, and much leſſe ought the conſecrate wine be ſould in bottels: <hi>In conſervatione pro infirmis,</hi> that is, in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2309:23"/>keeping the ſame for the ſicke, which a biding ſome time in the veſſell might be turned into vineger, &amp; ſo might ceaſe to be there the bloud of Chriſt, &amp; therfore ſhould not be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor yet conſecrated anew without a maſſe: <hi>addito quod in aestate bibliones aut muſcae generare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur,</hi> that is, in Summer, gnats &amp; flies would breede therin, although the veſſell were ſtopped never ſo cloſely: beſides, <hi>putreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret,</hi> that is, it would corrupte and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a thing abominable to be drunke, <hi>Et haec ratio</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gerſon,) est efficax valdè,</hi> It is a right ſubſtantiall &amp; knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reaſon, feare yee not.</p>
            <p>There are moe yet behind, but I had rather referre the reader vnto <hi>Gerſon</hi> himſelfe, who being for his time a verie learned man, was thought to doe this <hi>Ironicè,</hi> that is, cloſely girding at the councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> who being there in place, was inioyned by the Synod to ſet downe his minde herein.</p>
            <p>Q. Whie did Chriſt inſtitute the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the promiſe of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2309:23"/>Goſpel vnder the Signes of bread and wine?</p>
            <p>A. Forſooth, that by comparing of their ſeverall effects togeather, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their analogie,) the very force &amp; ſtrength of our faith might welneere ſenſiblie be perceaved, as whereby wee take holde, apprehend, keepe, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe in our harts &amp; mindes, the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed good thinges thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. VVhat is the <hi>analogie,</hi> by which worde is vnderſtood a likenes or proportion?</p>
            <p>A. As bread and wine, when man is in caſe to die and periſh for want of foode, do lift him vp againe, cheriſh, comfort, quicken and refreſh his languiſhed and fainting bodie: ſo our faith, ſure truſt, &amp; confidence repoſed in Chriſt, (who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered his body, powred forth, &amp; ſhed his bloud for the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes, when we were in caſe of miſery, wholie trodden downe and vanquiſhed of the Devill, and lying as it were groveling in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2309:24"/>our filthines) doth raiſe vs vp again, free vs from death, nouriſh, comfort, refreſh and quicken our farre, yea whole ſpent ſoules vnto life not temporal but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is the <hi>Coniunction,</hi> namelie of the Signe with the <hi>Thing</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a moſt true and ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, grounded on the promiſes of Chriſt, and wrought by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Is there no <hi>mutation</hi> then of the bread and wine: or at leaſt no phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical copulation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is no change of the Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in reſpect of their <hi>ſubſtaunce:</hi> but yet there is a mutation of them, in reſpect of the <hi>end. viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bread &amp; wine are no more novv prophane or common meate &amp; drinke, but do ſerue and are applied rather vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a proper, ſacramentall, and ſacred vſe and end.</p>
            <p>And that learned and worthy man <hi>M. Beza. Dial.</hi> 2. ſaith, that the myſtical
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2309:24"/>Symbols bread and wine, even after the ſanctifying of them, doe not leeſe their proper nature: For S. Paule, ſaith he, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen after the giuing of thankes calleth bread ſtil by the name of bread. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>vide locum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Can you inſtance in ſuch a change?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Verie wel. For wax which is affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces differeth nothing in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from that which is vnſealed: but in the vſe there is ſuch a change or alteration, that the one doth ſignifie &amp; confirme the writings whereto it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, whenas the other which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued and not applied to that vſe, doth not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If there be no phyſicall copulation or Conſubsta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiation as the Luthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hold, neither mutation of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Signes, which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts call tranſubſtantiation: why doth S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn Chap. 6. ſay that wee muſt eate the fleſh of Chriſt, and drinke his blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn doeth by this manner of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2309:25"/>ſpeaking ſet downe moſt perſpicuouſlie vnto the eies as it were of our ſoules the verie <hi>ſumme</hi> of the promiſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as namelie, what <hi>faith</hi> is, by which wee doe enioie thoſe promiſed good things: to the end, we might vnderſtand how the vertue thereof doth beareful ſway in our hearts cheering and lifting vs vp to buckle mightelie againſt the frontiers of ſinne, the world, and the Deuil.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then by this it ſeemeth, that to</hi> eate <hi>the fleſh of Chriſt, and to</hi> drinke <hi>his blood, are taken for one &amp; the ſelfe ſame thing, as to beleeue in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is ſo. And therefore S. <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaith plainely; <hi>Crede, &amp; manducaſti,</hi> that is, beleeue and thou haſt eaten.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But can you proue that to</hi> eate, <hi>and to</hi> beleeue, <hi>are one thing in the Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Eaſilie out of the ſixt chap. of <hi>Iohn</hi> and the 40. 47. verſes: as, <hi>verely, verely I ſay vnto you, hee that beleeveth in mee hath everlasting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:2309:25"/>
            <p>Now <hi>verſ.</hi> 51. of the ſame chap. hee expreſſeth this another way, that is, by <hi>eating of</hi> his fleſh. As, <hi>I am that living bread, which came downe from heaven: if any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for ever: and the bread that I will giue is my fleſh, which I will giue for the life of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you maie ſee, that both theſe manner of ſpeeches, though diverſe in words, yet al one in ſenſe and meaning, do obtaine likewiſe one &amp; the ſelfeſame promiſe, euen life eternal.</p>
            <p>Moreouer hence it riſeth, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times treating vpon the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord, do cite thoſe places out of the ſixt of <hi>Ioh;</hi> not that they thought the Lord to haue ſpoken there preciſely ſtrictlie or ſolelie of the Supper of the Lord: but that rather, becauſe in the right &amp; lawful vſe of the Supper, <hi>faith</hi> of the thing promiſed is there ſenſiblie, as one may ſay, expreſſed by the Lorde vnder the names of eating &amp; drinking: of which promiſe, the Supper is a pledg
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2309:26"/>and ſeale.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Seeing there is now no phyſicall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: doe wee receiue onlie the bare tokens of the things ſignified: or els are they</hi> effectuallie <hi>there gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For ſo much as Chriſt is the verie truth it ſelfe, and therfore moſt faithful in all his promiſes: ſo vndoubtedly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe made at his Supper, and as the Signes do repreſent, he maketh vs partakers of his verie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to make vs grow therby into one life with him. <hi>Calu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Chriſt is in heaven: (as, Act.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>verſe, ſci. VVhom the heaven muſt containe vntill the time, that all things be reſtored, beſides, looke all theſe places, as Hebr.</hi> 7.26. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.56. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.62. <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.33 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.69. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.51. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.12. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.) <hi>and we are heere Pilgrims on the earth. How then can this</hi> Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2309:26"/>
               <hi>of ſubstance bee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This <hi>Vnion</hi> is not in reſpect of the place; for ſo indeede is the body of Chriſt in <hi>Heauen</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptible: but it is in reſpect of our <hi>faith,</hi> by which we do worthily receiue this holy myſterie.</p>
            <p>For Chriſt, although he be in heaven according to his humane nature, and ſo ſitteth glorified at the right hand (<hi>Iohn</hi> 17.5.) of his Father, both our Mediatour and Interceſſour vnto God for vs: yet is hee alſo theſe fiue waies preſent in the earth with vs. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By his Godhead and Spirit.</item>
                  <item>2. By our <hi>faith</hi> in him.</item>
                  <item>3. By mutual loue.</item>
                  <item>4. By his vnion with humane nature, that is, in Coniunction of his Soule and body with ours.</item>
                  <item>5. By hope of our Conſummation &amp; glorification. Or,</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>According to others, thus; the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt now with vs, is twofolde; the one in reſpect of his perſon, the other in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2309:27"/>reſpect of his office.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Perſon,</hi> hee is with vs as true God filling both heauen and earth.</p>
            <p>In <hi>of fice,</hi> he is with vs by his <hi>grace</hi> &amp; <hi>Spirit. Math.</hi> 28.20. <hi>And loe, I am with you alway, vntill the end of the world. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> But Chriſt in his <hi>Humanity is not with vs,</hi> but ſo hee ſitteth at the right hand of the Father and of the throne of his Maieſtie in Heauen. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>So then this commeth to paſſe by the wonderous and vnſearchable wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Gods Spirit powring faith into vs, which faith coupling vs with the Son of God, cauſeth, that wee are more neerely ioined vnto the fleſh and blood of Chriſt, then we are vnto the bread which we eat, &amp; the wine which we drinke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Iuſt.</hi> For indeede ſuch is the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualnes of <hi>faith,</hi> which it hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the powerful working of Gods holy Spirit: that it doth moſt neerly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioine things, which are in place fartheſt remoued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2309:27"/>
            <p>Concerning this <hi>Coniunction</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ours with Chriſt, it is manifeſt that the Fathers doe all agree with this which hath bin ſaid, for the right recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and vnderſtanding of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and more eſpecially for the words of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. verſe</hi> 53.56. As, <hi>Then Ieſus ſaid vnto them, verely, verely I ſay vnto you, Except yee eate the fleſh of the Son of man, &amp; drinke his bloode, yee haue no life in you. He that eateth my fleſh, &amp; drinketh my blood, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in me, and I in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10. <hi>chap. verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>The cup of bleſsing which wee bleſse, is it not the Communion of the blood of Chriſt: the bread which we breake, is it not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body of Chriſt? For we that are many, are one bread and one bodie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are all partakers of one bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So yee ſee heere, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule ſaith that the bread, which we breake, is the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body of Chriſt, which is, it is the thing whereby we are recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into Communion and fellowſhip
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2309:28"/>with the body of Chriſt, and doe growe togither into one with him.</p>
            <p>Therfore al the Fathers iointly teach, that the very true fleſh of Chriſt, not that which was feigned of the Heretiks to be inviſible, but that which is like to ours in all things except ſinne, is truelie eaten of vs in the Supper of the Lord: &amp; is ſo eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we wholy grow into one whole Chriſt, how great ſoeuer we bee, being made fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30. See Zanchius in his treateſſe of ſpiritual wedlocke.</p>
            <p>Herevpon, ſaith <hi>Zanchius: Cyrill,</hi> and other of the Fathers affirmed that Chriſt dwelleth <hi>corporally and naturally</hi> in vs. Which words, ſaith he, muſt bee vnderſtoode, not of the <hi>manner</hi> howe Chriſt dwelleth in vs, as if he were in vs in any naturall and fleſhly manner: but they are to be vnderſtood of the <hi>things whereto</hi> we are vnited. For we are vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the true &amp; natural body of Chriſt and that by a true and <hi>reall</hi> vnion, but yet if you reſpect the manner how this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2309:28"/>is wrought; ſurely then it is accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and done by theſe two means, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> and by <hi>faith.</hi> Now this is farre of, I thinke, from that carnall, groſſe, and fleſhlie manner, which the Papiſts dreame of.</p>
            <p>This Doctrin, (touching our incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration into Chriſt by a ſpiritual ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner) all the Fathers taught. Wherefore <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin</hi> in his 50, tract vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohn: <hi>Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith he meaning the Iewes, heare &amp; lay hold of Chriſt, who ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They anſwere; whom ſhall I lay hould on? him that is abſent? Howe ſhal I lifte vp my hand into heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lay hold on him ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there? lift vp thy
<note n="*" place="margin">And in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church they vſed to ſay theſe words vnto the people. Surſum cor da in toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they were to pearce the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, (with St. Steven Act. 7 56.) by their faith, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Chriſt as he is man: and not in the earth.</note> 
               <hi>faith</hi> and thou haſt laid hold on him. Thy Fathers held him in the fleſh, doe thou holde him in thy <hi>heart:</hi> becauſe Chriſt beeing abſent is yet nevertheles alſo preſent. vnles he were preſent he could not be held of vs. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſheweth at large, that Chriſt is abſent in the fleſh, but is preſent with vs in <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:2309:29"/>
            <p>Whence it is manifeſt, that this <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is <hi>eſsentiall</hi> and <hi>reall,</hi> if we reſpect the thinges that are vnited, and the truth of the vnion: but if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the <hi>manner</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vel <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, how it is made, it is <hi>ſpirituall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat? is there no Coniunction the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where faith is not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Noe, doubtles; but a Sacramentall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction onely: which returneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to him that doth receine it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If it bee ſo, vvhy doth S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme thoſe to become guiltie of the bodie and blood of the Lord, vvhich doe eate this bread, and drinke the Cup vnworthelie.</hi> 1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 11.27. &amp; 1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 10.16.17.</p>
            <p>A. This may eaſily bee anſwered with the like, becauſe hee that beleeveth not the word of God, but heareth it vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, is guiltie of the word of God. For why, whoſoever beleeveth not, ſhal bee condemned. Looke <hi>Marke,</hi> 16.16. Item <hi>Iohn,</hi> 12. ca. verſ. 47.48.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Yea S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Austen hath the like kinde
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2309:29"/>of ſpeech; As he which eateth,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the bodie &amp; drinketh the blood of Christ vnvvorthely eateth and drinketh his owne da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation: ſo he, that receaveth Baptiſme vnvvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelie, receaveth iudgment and not ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Where this learned Father ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>ſacramentally,</hi> attributing vnto the Signe, the name of the thing it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Howe are the wicked then guilty of the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt: whenas they receave but the bare Elements or Signes alone?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Becauſe the diſgrace &amp; reproach, which they doe to the ſacred ſignes and ſymbols, doth redound even againſt the thinges themſelues ſignified thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Can you make this plaine and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar by ſome inſtance or other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes ſurely, it may be gathered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of affaires in this life. For whoſoever doth ſpue vpon, doth teare and trample vnder foote the Image or letters-Patents of an Emperour and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2309:30"/>mightie Prince, is foorthwith adiudged guiltie of hie treaſon: againe the ill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty or vſage of Embaſſadours doth returne and fall out vnto the contempt &amp; contumely of the king that ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But of how much ſorer puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe yee, (according to the Apoſtles wordes <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.) ſhal he be worthy, which treadeth vnder foote the Sonne of God, and counteth the bloode of the Teſtament as an vnholy thinge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was ſanctified, &amp; doth deſpight the Spirit of Grace? Looke beſides, 30.31. verſes of the ſame chap. Item. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. Item, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7. where you ſhall finde the like phraſes.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding it is but abſurdlie gathered out of 1. <hi>Corint,</hi> 11. chap. 27. verſ. that the vnbeleevers cannot ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee guiltie of the bodie and bloode of Chriſt, becauſe they doe not <hi>reallie</hi> eate Chriſt in the Sacrament; as though they could no otherwiſe be guiltie of it, and namely by their <hi>vnbeleife:</hi> whenas yet S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule ſpeaketh not there of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2309:30"/>but even of the verie belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers themſelues, vnrevere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly handling this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is the Meditation of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. This is twofold; conſiſting
<list>
                  <item>1. In the Endes.</item>
                  <item>2. In the Vſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are thoſe ſpeciall Endes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They be fiue: as;
<list>
                  <item>1. A reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Lords death.</item>
                  <item>2. A Sacrament of our incorporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>3. A Sacrament of our ſpiritual repaſt and nouriſhment.</item>
                  <item>4. A pledge of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givenes of ſinnes.</item>
                  <item>5. A bond &amp; true knotte of loue.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of theſe in order as they lie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi> Firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Supper of the Lord is <hi>memoria mortis,</hi> that is, a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ordained for a remembrance of the body of Chriſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2309:31"/>delivered vp to death for vs, and of his blood ſhedde for many for the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. ca. 26, v. deſcribeth this <hi>end</hi> moſt perſpicuouſlie: <hi>For as often</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as yee ſhall eate this bread, and drinke this Cup, yee ſhewe the Lords death till he come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Chriſt himſelfe. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22 <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>verſ. Doe this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in remembrance of mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuſtine</hi> the <hi>Martyr (Colloq. cum Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon. Apolog.</hi> 2.) ſaith that the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſticall</hi> bread is committed to vs <hi>ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordationem paſsionis Christi,</hi> that is, for a reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of the paſſion of Chriſt,</p>
            <p>Now marke heere, how ſhamefully the Papiſtes are beſides their beades in going wide from the marke and ende of the inſtitution. For Chriſt willeth vs to take this Sacrament, and to take bread and wine in <hi>remembrance</hi> of him.</p>
            <p>Therefore the bread is called the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt, not <hi>really,</hi> but in that it is a <hi>memoriall</hi> of his bodie, that is, the bread is a <hi>remembrance</hi> vnto vs of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2309:31"/>even as it is alſo commanded in the wordes of the inſtitution; <hi>hoc facite in mei commemorationem.</hi> Doe this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of mee. According to the truth whereof S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule is content to be ordered ſaying, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>mortem domini annunciatis vſquequo venerit;</hi> that is, ye ſhew the Lords death till hee come. Yea &amp; in the two former verſes; <hi>this doe yee in remembrance of me.</hi> But the Papiſts will not bee tied to this with the holy bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule,</hi> and therefore they wiſely invented another way, (which is a knacke more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie,) viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To make their Chriſt of bread.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To adore him in the bread: after they haue once made him, to eat part of him <hi>carnallie,</hi> &amp; <hi>groſly</hi> to reſerue part of him in their Pixes, for other holy vſes &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To offer him vp a Propitiatorie ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice <hi>pro viuis &amp; defunctis,</hi> both for the quicke and deade, as that pelting and peeviſh toy of theirs, <hi>Purgatorie</hi> I meane, an errour, yea an hereſie rather
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2309:32"/>being flatly againſt the Articles of our faith, doth teſtifie vnto vs.</p>
            <p>It is a Proverb, that a man ſhal ſoone know a ratte by his clawing: ſo may one as ſoone &amp; ſooner too ſmell out, (I will not ſay a knaue, it is to good a name for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,) what madd ſhavers theſe Papiſts are, by their ſtrange and vncooth do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. But to our purpoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againe.</p>
            <p>In the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we read that Chriſt bidding his Apoſtles to doe this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him, he did before verie apparently breake the bread. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the breaking of bread, is a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ceremonie for three cauſes, (for it ſignifieth the paſſion and ſeparation of his ſoule from the body:)</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Chriſt hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it: for it is a part of the <hi>Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe it tendeth to our Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, knowing that his bodie was brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>(Crucifixum non fractum)</hi> thus for our ſakes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That this monſter of <hi>tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> may bee taken away, according
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2309:32"/>to the iudgement of Vrſinus, pag. 688. and thus much of the firſt end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacramentum est incorporationis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strae,</hi> that is, it is a Sacrament of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporation into Chriſts body. And this is that which hath the promiſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.56. <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him.</hi> So <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 30. <hi>verſe. For wee are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his bodie, of his fleſh, and of his bones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacramentum est ſpiritualis nutritio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis noſtrae,</hi> that is, a Sacrament of our ſpiritual education and nutrition in the body of Chriſt. For as we are through Baptiſme waſhed with the bloode of Chriſt: ſo being waſhed and regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, wee are likewiſe continually nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the bodie and blood of Chriſt, as appeareth <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. <hi>cap. ver.</hi> 35, 53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>For ſo much as this our continuall nouriſhment in the body of Christ,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2309:33"/>floweth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe the head ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that by reaſon of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall mariage, coniunction, or vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him: ſet downe directly for our stay and comfort herein, places out of the holy ſcriptures for this ſo exceeding, excellent, and heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Looke, 1, Cor. 10, cap. 15, 16, 17. Iohn, 17, cap. 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 21, 22, 23 26, verſes, <hi>Item,</hi> Iohn, 15.4, 5, 6, 7.1, Cor. 12.12, 13, 14, <hi>Item,</hi> 1. Cor. 6.15, 16, 17 <hi>Item,</hi> 1, Iohn, 4 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, <hi>Item</hi> Eph. 2, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, <hi>Item</hi> Rev. 21, 2, <hi>Item</hi> Iſay, 54, 4, 5, 6, 7, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreouer I wil ſet downe theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath at large.</p>
            <p>Hoſe, 2, cap. 16, 19, verſes, <hi>And in that day</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>thou ſhalt cal me</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>my husband, and ſhalt call me no more</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>my Lord or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I will marry thee vnto mee for euer: yea I wil marry thee vnto mee in righteouſneſſe and in iudgement, and in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2309:33"/>mercie, and in compaſſion. And verſe 20. I will even marrie thee vnto mee in faithfulnes, and thou ſhalt knowe the Lord. Item <hi>Hoſe.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.3. <hi>verſe.</hi> Item 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.2. <hi>verſes. viz. VVould to God, yee could ſuffer a little my fooliſhnes, &amp; in deede, yee ſuffer mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For I am gealouſe over you with godlie gealouſie: for I haue prepared you for one husband, to preſent you as a pure Virgine to Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Ezch.</hi> 16. chapter but eſpecially theſe verſes following 6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13.14. viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And when I paſsed by thee, I ſaw thee polluted in thine owne bloode, and I ſaide vnto thee, when thou waſt in thy bloude, Thou ſhalt liue: even when thou waſt in thy blood, I ſaid vnto thee, thou ſhalt liue.</hi> I haue cauſed thee to multiplie, as the budde of the fielde, &amp; thou haſt encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and waxen great, and thou haſt got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten excellent ornaments, thy breaſtes are faſhioned, thine haire is growen, whereas thou waſt naked and bare.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2309:34"/>
            <p>Now when I paſſed by thee, and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon thee, behold, thy time was as the time of loue, &amp; I ſpredd my skirtes vpon thee, &amp; covered thy filthines: yea I ſware vnto thee, &amp; entered into a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with thee, ſaith the Lord God, and thou becameſt mine.</p>
            <p>Then waſhed I thee with water: yea, waſhed away thy blood from thee, and I annointed thee with oyle.</p>
            <p>I cloathed thee alſo with broithered worke, and ſhodde thee with badgers skinne: &amp; I girded thee about with fine linnen, and I covered thee with ſilke.</p>
            <p>I decked thee alſo with ornamentes, and I put bracelets vpon thine handes, and a chaine on thy necke.</p>
            <p>And I put a frontlett vpon thy face, and earings in thine eares, and a bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull crowne vpon thine head.</p>
            <p>Thus waſt thou deckte with golde &amp; ſilver, &amp; thy rayment was of fine linnen, and ſilke, and broidred worke: thou didſt eate fine floure, and honie, and oyle, &amp; thou waſt verie bewtifull, &amp; thou didſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2309:34"/>grow vp into a kingdome.</p>
            <p>And thy name was ſpred among the Heathen for thy bewtie: for it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect through my bewty, which I had ſet vpon thee ſaith the Lord God. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Item <hi>Zach.</hi> 1, <hi>chap:</hi> 14: <hi>Iſay</hi> 62.1. <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.1: 2: 3: 32: Can a maide forgett her ornament, or a bride her attire? yet my people haue forgotten mee, daies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number.</p>
            <p>Item <hi>Salomons</hi> ſonge, 2. cap. 5: verſe. <hi>Stay me with flagons, &amp; comfort me with apples: for I am ſicke of loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His left hand is vnder mine head, and his right hand doth embrace mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ibid. verſe 15.16. Take vs the foxes, the little foxes, which deſtroy the vines: for our vines haue ſmale grapes.</p>
            <p>My welbeloued is mine, &amp; I am his: he feedeth among the Lillies.</p>
            <p>Item, <hi>Cant,</hi> 5, <hi>cap,</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. And <hi>Cant,</hi> 7, <hi>cap,</hi> 10, 12, <hi>verſes,, I am my welbeloueds, &amp; his deſire is towards mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Item, <hi>Iohn,</hi> 6.35, 47, 48, <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 3.15, <hi>Heb,</hi> 3, 14.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2309:35"/>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Revelation,</hi> 3. <hi>cap,</hi> 20, <hi>verſe</hi> as, <hi>Behold, I stand at the doore, &amp; knocke, if any man heare my voice, and open the doore, I will come in vnto him, and vvill ſuppe with him, and he with mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>Revel:</hi> 12: <hi>ca:</hi> 1, 2, <hi>verſe. And there appeared a great wonder in heaven: a woman cloathed with the Sunne, &amp; the Moone was vnder her feete, &amp; vpon her head a Crowne of</hi> 12 <hi>starres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſhee was vvith childe, and cried traveyling in birth, &amp; was pained readie to bee delivered.</hi> This is not properlie meant (as ſome will) of the <hi>Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but of the Chruch, for theſe reaſons;</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Church is in this manner of ſpeaking figured out aptly vnto our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceavance vnder the name of moone: as alſo Chriſt is by the word <hi>Sunne, Mal.</hi> 4</p>
            <p n="2">2 From a certaine relation betwixt the Sun &amp; the moone. For the moone is a leſſer light, yea which borroweth al her light from the Sunne: ſo this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or church being the weaker veſſell reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon Chriſt her ſtrength &amp; ſtay, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2309:35"/>whome as from a loving husband, ſhee receaveth all her glorie.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, in this moſt ſacred and inviolable mariage betweene Chriſt &amp; his Church, we muſt note three eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things; 1. The precontract: 2. The ſolemnization: 3. The full accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vpſtroke thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the precontract is done by the immediate working of the holy Ghoſt, powring faith into our hearts, by which we willingly giue our conſent.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſolemnizing heereof was and is celebrated both in the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the old and new law; as then by Circumciſion, Paſchall lambe: now by Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper: where all the graces of Chriſt the true and faithfull huſband of his church, are and were as in a rich Treaſure-houſe moſt firmely ſealed, confirmed, &amp; made vnto vs on his behalfe: and where we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine our ſelues, doe plight moſt invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably, our owne fidelitie and obeyſance to him.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2309:36"/>
            <p>Thirdly, the conſummation or the accompliſhment and vpſtroake hereof is done two kinde of waies; 1. In the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of this our earthly Tabernacle: 2. In the ful particular enioying the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the lambe our Bridegroome, whenas we ſhal behold him as he is, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen face to face.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall this woman (which is the Church) be truely &amp; perfectly cloathed with the Sun, that is, ſhee ſhal be clad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with the rich and glorious robes of Chriſts owne righteouſnes. And this muſt bee vnderſtoode two waies as the Schoolemen hold; <hi>tam privativè quàm poſitivè.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, is a not imputing, that is, a pardoning &amp; forgiuenes of our ſinnes, by which we are let to goe ſcotfree and are deliuered as wel from the guiltines of ſinne, as from the puniſhment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, namely, death eternall.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is an imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt his righteouſnes, by which even for the righteouſnes of Chriſt attributed vnto
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2309:36"/>vs through <hi>Faith</hi> and made ours by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, we are allowed for <hi>iuſte</hi> in the ſight of God, and which is more, we are accompted worthie to aſcend vp into the high habitation of the moſt omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent and mightie <hi>Iehovah,</hi> even into that moſt holy hill of Sion &amp; new Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.12. <hi>cap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This thing doth David point out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 32.1, 2. verſes as, <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>is hee whoſe vvickednes is forgiven, and whoſe ſin is covered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſsed is the man, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord imputeth not iniquity, &amp; in whoſe Spirit there is no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, behold <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a definitiue, certaine, &amp; reſolute <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:</hi> the ſumme wherof is, that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes of man doth conſiſt in the remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of ſinnes and in the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, whoſe effect is <hi>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctification,</hi> which is taught in the end of the ſecond v: <hi>&amp;</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2309:37"/>
            <p>Now <hi>Iuſtification</hi> is heere declared in a threefolde manner:</p>
            <p n="1">1 That our ſinnes be ſo taken away, as that they are not.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That they are ſo covered, as not the prints &amp; filth thereof may appeare. v. 7.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That God doth not impute them, after he hath taken them away, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth onely the righteouſnes in Chriſt by <hi>faith,</hi> as did vnto our father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 15. <hi>ca.</hi> 6. <hi>v. And Abraham be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved the Lord, &amp; he cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted that to him for righteouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, we ſee nowe that by vertue of this our Mariage with CHRIST, we are inveſted &amp; covered with Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, and cloathed vppon with the garments (<hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. reade the chapter) of his righteouſnes. Looke <hi>Ierem.</hi> 23. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.7.8.</p>
            <p>And hence is it, whie S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paule</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs ſo inſtantly to put on the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>As, Rom.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 3.10.12. Againe, 1. <hi>Theſ</hi> 5.8. we are willed to put on the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2309:37"/>breſtplate of faith, &amp; loue, and the hope of ſalvation for an helmet. For by this faith we are miſtically inſerted &amp; vnited into Chriſt, ſeeing he is the vine it ſelfe, we are the braunches: he is the tree, we the fruit: he the Sunne, we the beames: he is the head, wee the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers: he is the Bridegrome, &amp; we the Spouſe.</p>
            <p>This eſpouſage and coniunction is ſo ſure, as ſhal not, nay ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be diſſolved. For the Spirite of GOD is the Scribe, which drawes the bandes betwixte vs: the word of God is the band: his mercy, the ſeale: the deliverance, benefite, and freedome that wee haue by it, is our peace. Peace with God, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vs to himſelfe in Chriſt: peace with our neighbour in ſhewing all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Chriſtian charity now vnto him: peace with our owne ſelues, not daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any more with the dreadful horrour and power of the Devill: Laſtly, peace againſt our enemies, nothing apalled nor fearing, what man can doe vnto vs. For if God be on our ſide, who then can
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2309:38"/>be againſt vs. <hi>Rom,</hi> 8. wherefore ſuch &amp; ſo great is this faith &amp; the force therof, that it is called a breſtplate, a ſhield, yea even victorie it ſelfe. 1, <hi>Ioh,</hi> 5, <hi>Ca,</hi> 4, ver. And right excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſpeaketh a learned man heereof: <hi>Fide, inquit, tantum poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quantum credimus,</hi> that is, By faith wee can doe ſo much, how much vvee doe beleeue.</p>
            <p>But wheras we are vnited vnto Chriſt by faith, we muſt not miſconceaue, and vnderſtand preſently a bare, hiſtoricall, temporarie, or idle faith, that is to faie, dead in it ſelfe: but rather that which is accompanied or attended on from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide by all good works, namely, a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying, a liuely, an effectual, a working, and fruitful faith. It muſt not be like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe appels me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> which grewe in the place of Sodome &amp; comorrha: ſuch as ſhewed faire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but ſo ſoone as one toucheth them <hi>[tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeunt in fumum,]</hi> they vaniſh away to nothing. But, <hi>is verè credit</hi> (as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeaketh) <hi>qui verè exercet opera bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2309:38"/>credendo</hi> that is, hee doth beleeue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, who in beleeving is carefull to ſhew forth good workes with all.</p>
            <p>It behooveth vs therfore now, being receaved into the favour of God againe by &amp; through Chriſt: that we leeſe not the ſame any more, but let vs lay ſure hold on our Lord &amp; Sauiour, and as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon Luc.</hi> 2.28. tooke him vp in his armes: ſo let vs take him vp alſo not in our armes without, but inwardly in our heartes, and then may we boldly come before, and praiſe his holy name.</p>
            <p>One ſometime that could not tell how to eſcape loſſe of life from a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine king, becauſe the king was provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked againſt him, tooke vp the kings ſon, who was enwrapte with the loue which he bare to his ſonne, that he cleane for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the hatred hee bare to his enemie: ſo we muſt pray Chriſt Ieſus to bee our advocate to his Father, beeing aſſured that God is well pleaſed in him, and we muſt take CHRIST as it were in our armes, and then God looking on vs, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2309:39"/>our ſinnes. For by this means it will come to paſſe, that wee ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to reioyce at all times, yea even then, when God is ſaide to iudge the worlde with righteouſneſſe. For though wee bee not righteous in our ſelues: yet Chriſtes righteouſnes is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for ours.</p>
            <p>And as Parents loue their children, though they bee never ſo deformed: ſo God louing his Sonne lookes on vs, and loues vs. This is called (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13, 14, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3, 27,) a putting on of Chriſt. And as <hi>Iacob</hi> hauing putte on <hi>Eſaues</hi> apparell wan the bleſſing: ſo wee putting on Chriſts garments of righteouſnes ſhall obtaine the bleſſing and fauour of God for evermore.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, vnto this our ſpirituall mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and coniunction, it ſhall not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenient to annexe three neceſſarie obſeruations, rules, or concluſions; as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, this coniunction, heere ſpoken of, muſt be <hi>ſubſtantiall</hi> or <hi>eſſentiall,</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2309:39"/>not only <hi>energeticall,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall:</hi> namely whole man with whole Chriſt (yea and by meanes of him) even with the whole Trinitie and Godhead. <hi>See theſe places.</hi> 2, <hi>Epiſt, Pet,</hi> 1, <hi>cap,</hi> 4, <hi>ver, Ioh,</hi> 17, 22, 23, <hi>Ioh,</hi> 14, 23. 1, <hi>Ioh,</hi> 4, <hi>ca,</hi> 12, 13, 15, 16. <hi>v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, it muſt be <hi>reall</hi> &amp; <hi>true,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not imaginatorie or accidentall: namely as the braunches with the vine, as the ſtones of the wall with the whole building, as the members of mans body with the head, and as the coupling of man and wife [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] in one fleſh (according to Gods ordinance) be they never ſo far a ſunder in reſpect of place. <hi>Epheſ,</hi> 5, <hi>cap,</hi> 29, 30.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, which muſt ever diligentlie be marked; It muſt, (<hi>quoad modum,</hi> that is, in reſpect of the <hi>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner</hi>) be a ſpiritual, and no corporall or carnall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction.</p>
            <p>This is over hard to bee comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of fleſh and bloud, nay it ſurpriſeth cleane mans ſenſe, his witte, and reaſon: in-ſomuch, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paule</hi> himſelfe, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2309:40"/>it (<hi>Epheſ,</hi> 5, 32. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a great ſecret,, which we cannot attaine vnto but by a ſure and liuely (<hi>Epheſ,</hi> 3, <hi>cap,</hi> 3, 9, <hi>v,</hi>) faith: yea which is more, the verie Angels themſelues [1. <hi>Pet,</hi> 2, <hi>cap,</hi> 12, <hi>verſ,</hi>] doe deſire <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicere,</hi> that is, to behold or (more neerely to the Greeke word) to ſee and prie into this myſtery of the ſalvation of mankind, purchaſed and wrought by Chriſt, wherof this ſpirituall vnion with him is the very ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, intereſt, &amp; earneſt of the holie Ghoſt give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his elect chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for their moſt ful aſſurance, which they doe encloſe &amp; lay vp in their harts by <hi>faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhal one ſay then to theſe buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſardly Papiſts, that bee they convinced by the ſcriptures never ſo plainely, yea though the Apoſtle <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule</hi> ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully endewed with the Spirit, doth not omitte to ſay and confeſſe that it is a great myſterie: moreover that the holy Angels too the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues do even long to know this ſecret: yet for all this they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2309:40"/>are nevertheleſſe caried and ledd away ſtill with a carnall or fleſhly vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this ſo ſpiritual &amp; deepe a myſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie, avouching that they doe eate <hi>orally</hi> the tranſubſtantiated bodie of Chriſt made by the cunning ſlipper-deviſe and incantation (I ſhould haue ſaide conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,) of the maskinglike attired maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing-Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we haue handled the three firſt ſpecial endes of the Lords Supper, the two latter whereof tended to our myſticall incorporation or inauguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt, as alſo vnto a ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt &amp; food, wherby we gather ſtrength and growe vp continually from faith (<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7.) to faith, vntill we bee made a perfect man in him.</p>
            <p>It reſteth now that we ſhould declare the two other ends, but that preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vrgeth vs to interlace certain rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt the orall &amp; fleſhely eating of Chriſtes body in the Sacrament, with the abſurdities, that doe riſe therevpon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. You ſaid before in the third ſpeciall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2309:41"/>ende, that this Supper is a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our ſpirituall nouriſhment: do you then make a difference of eating, ſeeing you adde, ſpirituall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is right meete ſo to diſtinguiſh, leaſt wee ſhoulde bee caried away with the ſweepe of groſſe errour, as to to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny are. For <hi>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducatio</hi> or eating is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſacramentall: ſometime ſpiritual onely: ſometime both ſpiritual &amp; ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>VVhat is ſacramentalleating?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the externall &amp; ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible eating &amp; drinking of the bread &amp; wine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is ſpirituall eating?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is that, which is done onely by faith, and it anſwereth <hi>(ex oppoſito)</hi> vnto that firſt: which is nothing elſe but a ſigne &amp; ſymball heereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Then theſe two are not alwaies ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned togither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. For as the externall &amp; cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall eating may be without the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual: ſo the ſpiritual alſo may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2309:41"/>the externall. As ſaith <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Auſten, de Ciuit lib.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the Sacramentall &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eating togither?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the very right vſe of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which is required in the inſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is carnall eating convinced by the word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt himſelfe doth overthrow it by two arguments, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 62.63. <hi>v.</hi> The one drawen from the ſigne: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the vſe. viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A ſigno,</hi> or from the <hi>ſigne:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth this offend? what then, ſaith he, if yee ſhould ſee the Sonne of man aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vp where he was before? Signify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therby (as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> rightly think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) that his aſcenſion &amp; carnall eating of his fleſh can in no wiſe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d togither.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ah vſu,</hi> that is, from the <hi>vſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the Spirit, (ſaith he,) that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: the fleſh profiteth nothing: the wordes that I ſpeake vnto you are <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and <hi>life.</hi> That is, (as the naturall and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2309:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>proper ſenſe of the Text inferreth,) ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall eating is vnprofitable: but the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall doth giue life and quickneth.</p>
            <p>Now the Papiſtes doe checke theſe words of Chriſt, and cavill ſtoutly, or rather ſtubburnely &amp; ſpitefully with vs, that it is the orall &amp; fleſhly chamming and grinding of Chriſt betwixte their teeth, that profiteth.</p>
            <p>But it is in vaine to reaſon the cauſe which theſe drawe-latches and corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurkers. For as the Proverbe goes; an Ape will be an Ape ſtill, putt him into a coate of velvet or what you will: ſo is a Papiſt no changling in opinion, but will liue and die a Papiſt, ſpeake, write, read, reaſon, or do what ye liſt, nay what you can.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding how obſtinate and ſelfe-willingly wedded ſoever they bee to their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: yet it ſtandeth vs great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon, to be obedient and yeeld vnto the truth, demonſtrated vnto vs by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable teſtimonies out of Gods moſt holy word, &amp; let vs pray the Lord both
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2309:42"/>night &amp; day to be conſtantly grounded and eſtabliſhed heerein. And in deede it is a ſhame for vs to bee inferiour to our Adverſaries heerein, which are ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedly &amp; ſtiffely nayled vnto their ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarie deviſes &amp; dreames of men; who after ſaying once, <hi>it is my Conſcience,</hi> looke for no more, they haue told you all: it is a ſhame, I ſay, of all ſhames, that wee ſhould not moſt reſolutely liue and die heerein. For wee haue more to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge for our ſelues, then, <hi>It is my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> (and who knowes not that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience muſt bee grounded on ſcience, which ſcience too commeth from the word of God, otherwiſe it will proue but a bare buckle and thong, that is a verie meere conceipte.) For wee haue theſe three thinges to ſtand in our behalfe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt the worde of God which is truth it ſelfe &amp; cannot lie this they haue not, becauſe they derogate therefrom, ſaying, that the authority of their church is aboue the ſame, yea they ſticke not to make their traſhie traditions equal with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2309:43"/>it, yea they abuſe it and blaſpheme it with the rankeſt Atheiſtes of our time, the one tearming it a noſe of waxe, a ſhipmans hoſe, a blackincky Goſpel: the other belching out this blaſphemie, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing it to be no more but a wittie poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of wiſe men to keepe fooles in awe: but let them walke togither as never a barrell of them better hering.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Beſides the word which is our warrant from God himſelfe, wee haue alſo his holy Spirit to aſcertaine vs therein, powring faith into our heartes, whereby we do aſſuredly beleeue it: this they haue not neither, becauſe they rob him of his proper effect and operation, which is immediatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Father &amp; the Sonne to illighten our minds giving to vs the right meaning and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his worde, which they moſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly appropriate to their Pope, whoſe power is ſuch, as that he may racke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his pleaſure. And no marveile, ſeeing they haue made a quarter God of him, to rule the roſt in the world as his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2309:43"/>liſteth, according to this blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous verſe of him.
<q>
                  <l>Oraclô voc is mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di moderaris habenas,</l>
                  <l>Et merito in terris crederis eſſe Deus.</l>
               </q> Yea, hee is become ſuch a ſawcie Syr, that he can change the Articles of faith and giue auctority to general councels, as it is ſaide:
<q>Articulos ſoluit, ſynodum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> facit ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralem</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly &amp; laſtly, Beſides the word and ſpirit of God, we haue our owne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is, our whole ſoule and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to teſtifie with vs that what we do, we do it as his adopted children, that is, not hypocritically, but faithfully, truly, and ſincerely.</p>
            <p>This doth <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule</hi> teach, <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.16. <hi>The ſame Spirit beareth witnes with our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that we are the children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let them then caſt of this deceavea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maske of a ſleeueles and pretended conſcience of theirs, and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it on Gods word, deſiring him to vonchſafe them of his Spirit to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2309:44"/>their mindes, nowe darkened with errours and ſuperſtition, that ſo, they may ioine togither in one with vs, to profeſſe &amp; beleeve the ſame. Which I pray God to graunt, according to his good pleaſure and will.</p>
            <p>But to the Purpoſe, where I doe mean to ſhew partly <hi>ab impoſsibili,</hi> that is from the vnpoſſibilitie of the thinges partly a <hi>conſequente abſurdo,</hi> that is, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the notorious abſurdities which muſt follow: that this carnal eating may not nor cannot at any rate ſtand with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogie of faith, which was as effectuall vnto the Fathers before Chriſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: as it is to vs ſince his comming.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt cannot bee receaved or ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten but after a carnal and groſſe kinde: then I pray how did the Patriarkes and Fathers eate Chriſt? whenas <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 53. our Saviour Chriſt ſaith; <hi>Verely, verelie I ſaie vnto you, vnleſſe yee ſhall eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his bloud, yee haue no life in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the fathers had life in them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2309:44"/>they had an vndoubted faith in Chriſt to come; which was as effectuall to them for their ſalvation &amp; receiving vp into glorie: (as was <hi>Enoch, Heb.</hi> 11, <hi>cap</hi> 5, <hi>verſ.</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> 2, <hi>Kings.</hi> 2, <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>verſe.</hi>) as our faith is effectual in him, now that he is come. For which cauſe they muſt needes grant another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of eating, differing altogither from car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, which is ſpirituall onely &amp; done by faith.</p>
            <p>Now, as they did eat Chriſt then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not yet come in the fleſh ſo doe, nay ſo muſt wee alſo eate him nowe, (for if there be any difference, it is in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Signes not in Subſtance,) as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule</hi> wel declareth, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 <hi>c.</hi> 1.2.3.4. <hi>verſes: viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover, brethren, I would not that ye ſhould be ignorant, that all our Fathers were vnder the cloud, &amp; al paſsed through the ſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, And did all drinke the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall drinke (for they dranke of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2309:45"/>Rocke that followed them: and the Rocke was Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to which ſpirituall kinde of eating both ours and theirs, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten</hi> ſaith thus; <hi>Vt quid dentes &amp; ventre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paraſti: crede &amp; manducaſti,</hi> that is, why haſt thou prepared teeth &amp; a bellie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and thou haſt eaten.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ab Abſurdo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the Philoſopher, that is, grant one abſurditie, and others do follow ſtraight vpon. Wherefore if the reprobate ſhould eate the body of Chriſt: al theſe and a great many moe abſurdities muſt needes follow; as that the reprobate are made the members of Chriſt, that the reprobate are ingraffed into the bodie of Chriſt, that Chriſt doth dwell in the reprobate, that they can bee made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chriſt &amp; Belial togither, which is horrible to ſpeake. For which cauſe one ſaith: <hi>Iudam panem Domini, ſed non panem Dominum comediſse,</hi> that is, Iudas did eate the bread of the Lord, but hee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2309:45"/>did not eate bread the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſons againſt carnall eating.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make ſhort of the matter, theſe reaſons following doe all make againſt carnal eating of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, he tooke a true humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: ſo that we can eate him no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then did his diſciples in the firſt ſupper.</p>
            <p>But here do the <hi>Vbiquitaries</hi> giue vs the ſlippe, wringing themſelues out of the briars with a ſophiſme <hi>de falſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecto elenchi;</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they teach that Chriſt in theſe words of the ſupper, <hi>take, eate:</hi> gaue commaundement for the orall or fleſhly eating of his bodie: &amp; yet thoſe wordes are not ſpoken of the body of Chriſt, becauſe hee tooke not that into his hands, neither did he breake his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and giue it to his diſciples: but they are ſpoken <hi>de pane,</hi> of the bread, which he tooke into his hand, over which hee gaue thankes, which he brake and gaue to his diſciples.</p>
            <p>But againſt this &amp; ſuch like dotages
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2309:46"/>of theirs Chriſt himſelfe forewarneth his diſciples, that they ſhould not ſuffer themſelues to bee deluded therewith, <hi>Math.</hi> 24. <hi>cap</hi> 23.24.25. <hi>verſes. viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then if any ſhall ſay vnto you, Lo here is Chriſt, or there, beleeue it not. For there ſhal ariſe falſe Chriſts, &amp; falſe prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and wonders, ſo that if it were poſsible, they ſhoulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the very elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold, I haue told you before.</hi> See 26, 27, 28, verſes of the ſame Chap.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, he aſcended viſibly from the earth into heauen: where he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth til the time that al things be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which God hath ſpoken by the mouth of al his holy Prophets ſince the world beganne. <hi>Act</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, ſuch is our eating of him, as his dweliing is in vs: but he dwelleth in vs by faith. Eph. 3. cap. 17. As, <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your harts, by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, al the Saints both of the old and new Teſtament haue one &amp; the ſame vnion with Chriſt, which is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2309:46"/>
            <p n="5">5. Fiftly, Chriſt onlie is able to offer himſelfe vnto the Father for vs, &amp; nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the helpe of any man.</p>
            <p>Bluſh then yee frapling maſſing-Prieſtes to offer him vp ſo often by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a common art amongſt you, and remember what a grievous accompt ye are to render for thus crucifying againe vnto your ſelues the Sonne of God, and making a mocke of him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. cap. 6. <hi>v.</hi> Which place though it be directly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt ſuch as doe malitiouſlie and finally ſpurne at the truth of the good word of God, after they haue taſted thereof, and beene once lightned and made partakers of the holy Ghoſt: yet apply it to your ſelues, who though yee doe not quite forſake the word: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding yee doe alter the word by gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and corrupting the perfect ſenſe and meaning thereof, as your Rhemiſh Teſtament can witneſſe it here to your faces, and elſewhere (except yerepent) to your endleſſe deriſion and ſhame.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:2309:47"/>
            <p>Wel as you alter the word, ſo yee add &amp; diminiſh too, the one by bringing in an hundred knacks of knauerie, as Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie hole, praier for the dead, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto Saints; I wil not ſpeake of your paradoxes, <hi>ſcil.</hi> Children dying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out baptiſme are al condemned, <hi>ad pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam damni,</hi> as ye cal it, but not <hi>ad paena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſus;</hi> of your <hi>Limbus Patrum</hi> before Chriſts comming, of your innumerable Maſſes, dirges, Trentals, Popes Pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Canons, Decretal Epiſtles which you make to be authentical with the worde of God. Theſe be your owne additions, wee cannot tel what to doe with them, and therfore take them home to you &amp; ſweepe your chymnies with them.</p>
            <p>Doe ye aſke me wherein ye do dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh? I neede neither goe farre a field for this; ſeeing yee diminiſh from the very inſtitution it ſelfe of Chriſt, by taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cuppe from the Laitie: yee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh it, when yee doe ſo impudentlie impaire the credit and autoritie by cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiving it to your owne helliſh cenſures
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2309:47"/>and moſt ouglie practiſes. But remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, (if ye be not voide yet of al feeling) what is denounced againſt al ſuch wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; heynous practitioners, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22 <hi>cap.</hi> 18, 19, <hi>verſes. Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12, 32, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30, 6. <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> 1, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wil paſſe ouer to ſpeake how the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes doe diminiſh from the office of Chriſt the one and onlie mediatour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man, (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.) by imperfecting ſtil of that, which hee by one oblation &amp; ſacrifice of himſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe hath made for euer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>Heb</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. <hi>VVherefore he is able perfectly</hi> to ſaue them that come vnto God <hi>by him,</hi> ſeeing he euer liueth, to make interceſſion for them. Againe, that Chriſts one only ſacrifice is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent without this toyiſh elevating him in their Hoſt, looke theſe places: as,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10, 15, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2, 17, 18, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4, 14, 15, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5, <hi>cap.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, <hi>verſes, Heb.</hi> 9, <hi>cap.</hi> 11, 12, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, <hi>verſes, Heb.</hi> 10.10, 14, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5, 2, <hi>Item Mark.</hi> 10, 45, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:2309:48"/>
            <p>And <hi>Heb.</hi> 8, <hi>cap.</hi> 4, <hi>verſe,</hi> Jt is moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently taught, (which I woulde haue thoroughly and thoroughly to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,) that if Chriſt were on the earth, he were not then a Prieſt, ſeeing (ſaith he) there are Prieſts that according to the law offer giftes, who ſerue vnto the patterne of heauenlie things, as Moſes was warned by God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was about to finiſh the Tabernacle: See, ſaid hee, that thou make all things according to the patterne, ſhewed thee in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p>Further, 2, <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, <hi>cap,</hi> 16, <hi>ver. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> henceforth know we no man after the fleſh, yea though wee had knowne Chriſt after the fleſh, yet nowe hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth know we him no more.</p>
            <p>Firſt then by theſe two places wee finde, that if Chriſt were on the earth now in his humane nature, he could be no Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, that we may not hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth knowe him any more after the fleſh, much leſſe as Papiſtes ſo groſly minded would, to eate him <hi>fleſhly.</hi> But
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2309:48"/>the Papiſts being ſo ſlipper as any eele, doe whip in and out by the backe dore, ſaying: that Chriſtes body is vpon the earth <hi>per modum inviſibilem,</hi> that is, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an inviſible manner but this deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not worth the ſmoke of a ladle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſts body is not anie where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, ſeeing it is wholy againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a bodie. For once take away the proper adiunct: and take the Subiect af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I haſten to the other reaſons.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Sixtly</hi> The bleſſings promiſed in the Supper are ſpiritual.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Seventhly</hi> and laſtly, The Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the ſigne with the thing ſignified doth manifeſtly refell tranſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: becauſe it were not a Sacrament at all, did it not conſiſt of theſe two thinges, the ſigne and the thing ſignified. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt notable is that ſaying of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius</hi> the <hi>Moonke: Bread &amp; wine</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>are a correſpondent type of his fleſh, and they who receaue the bread vvhich is ſhewed, eate the fleſh of Christ ſpiritually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hither to of the reaſons: I wil returne
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2309:49"/>to the two other ſpecial endes of the Supper yet remaining behinde, namely the 4. and the 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fourth Ende.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is that, that ſtandeth vs inſteeed as a pledge of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that is, of the promiſe of <hi>forgiuenes</hi> of ſinnes. And ſo are the verie wordes of the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Math.</hi> 26. <hi>ca.</hi> 28. <hi>ver. For this is my blood</hi> of the new Teſtament, that is ſhedd for many, for the <hi>remiſſion</hi> of ſinnes. So do the wordes implie, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>verſ. This Cuppe is the newe Testament in my blood, which is ſhedd for you:</hi> That is, This Cup is a pledge &amp; ſeale of the promiſe of remiſſion of ſinnes purchaſed for you by the ſhedding of my bloode.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Places for remiſsion of ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. cap. 5. And yee know that he appeared that hee might take away our ſinnes, and in him is no ſinne.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.10. Herein is loue, not that we loved God but that he loued vs, and ſent his ſonne to be a reconciliation for our <hi>ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2309:49"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſayas,</hi> 44. <hi>ca.</hi> 21.22. <hi>ver.</hi> Remember theſe (ô <hi>Iacob</hi> and Iſrael) for thou art my ſervant: I haue formed thee: thou art my ſervant: ô Iſrael forget mee not. I haue put away thy tranſgreſſions like a cloude, and thy ſinnes as a miſte, turne vnto mee, for I haue redeemed thee.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> If we acknowledge our ſinnes, he is faithful and iuſt, to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue</hi> vs our ſinnes, &amp; to clenſe vs from all vnrighteouſnes.</p>
            <p>Looke theſe places: <hi>Micheas,</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.31. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.13.14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.29. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1.2.3.4. <hi>verſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fift ende.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is <hi>Vinculum dilectionis,</hi> that is, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of our mutual <hi>ſociety</hi> amongſt our ſelues, as the members of one &amp; the ſame bodie, whoſe head is Chriſt; (and not the Pope, as the Papiſts doe <hi>paulter</hi> and keepe an illfavourd coyle about it.) For theſe places commonſtrate Chriſt to be our head alone.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.17. <hi>ver. Coloſs.</hi> 1.18.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2309:50"/>
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.30. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15.16. As for the Pope, let him be an head where hee can currie favour beſt: wee for our parts are abſolutely prohibited by Chriſt our onely head, to become the members of an harlotte according to the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> much more are we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to make our ſelues the bodie of that ſpiritual ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet &amp; whore of Rome, that is, to receave the marke, or the name of the beaſt, or the number of his name, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from hence, (by reaſon of that ſtrict co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion between al the Saints, which commeth wholie from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of our coniunction with Chriſt,) is ſet forth that Chriſtian band of loue betweene the Spouſe and Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1, <hi>cap,</hi> 3, <hi>v.
<note n="*" place="margin">Fide adhe remus Chriſto: di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectione tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſto, tum nobis ipſis mutuò 1. Cor. 10. ca. 16. 17. v. Epheſ. 4.3.4. 1: Cor. 12.12. ad finem cap. 13. Epheſ. 3.6.9. Rom. 13.8. Coloſ. 3.14. Rom. 8.17.</note> Drawe mee, wee will runne after thee.</hi> Where note preſently vpon the ſingular number followeth the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. For the Church is as one building, but many ſtones: one wine, but many grapes: one bread, but many graines: to be ſhort, one body &amp; yet many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2309:50"/>
               <hi>VVherfore loue is the very bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> that is, <hi>by which we both worſhip God in a liuly faith, &amp; do likwiſe loue our ſelues moſt ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly &amp; ſincerely. Fran. Iun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly adde this one Ende more: <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonium Reſurrection is eſt,</hi> that is, It is a ſure teſtification of our <hi>reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> by the vertue of Chriſt rayſed againe. For he is our head, and therfore wil raiſe vs vp to bliſſe, which are his members.</p>
            <p>And in ſooth vnto this ſtring or bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch tend all the former. For which cauſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Ioh</hi> 6. <hi>cap,</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ver. VVhoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever eateth my fleſh, &amp; drinketh my blood, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Thus much of the endes, which are the firſt parte of the Meditation of the Lords Supper: vvherein doth the ſecond conſist?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the right vſe thereof, viz.</p>
            <p>A right and ſincere <hi>examination</hi> of our owne ſelues: by which we are either to be receaved to it, or excluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it.</p>
            <p>That we may be admitted thervnto;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2309:51"/>we muſt conſider whether wee bee the true members of Chriſt, or no. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paule</hi> giueth vs this rule to follow, 1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 11. <hi>cap,</hi> 28, <hi>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let every man therfore examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and let him ſo eate of this bread, &amp; drinke of this Cuppe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For he that eateth &amp; drinketh vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, eateth and drinketh his owne dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, becauſe hee diſcerneth not the Lords body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is ſaide to diſcerne the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, who hath a iuſt regard of the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes thereof: and therfore doth with due reverence come and draw neere to eate the foode of his Soule.</p>
            <p>2, <hi>Corint,</hi> 13. <hi>ca,</hi> 5. <hi>verſe,</hi> the Apoſtle doth explaine his minde perfectly, how this examination ſhould be had:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proue your ſelues, vvhether yee are in the faith: examine your ſelues: knovv yee not your ovvne ſelues, hovve that Ieſus Chriſt is in you, except yee be reprobats?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which words he doth moſt pithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2309:51"/>exhort the people of Corinth, and in them all Chriſtians, that they would or ſhould rather now, not onely abſtaine from ſchiſmes and vnreverent gurman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing and feaſting, as though this were ſufficient, (&amp; no more a do to be made) vnto the worthy receaving of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: but he proceedeth a degree higher, and teacheth how that everie man ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth bound in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, to deſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very depth and ſecrets of his hart and thoughts, and in a moſt narrow and orderly ſort, to ſieft as it were, to ſearch, and trie himſelfe throughly; as namelie, whether he doth fullie &amp; reſolutely, (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath ſorrowed for his ſinnes paſt) beleeue in Chriſt the onely Mediatour and ſatisfier of Gods wrath for our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes committed: whether he hath an earneſt intent and purpoſe to hate ſinne ever afterward, and to live iuſtly, holily, and purely, that hee may ſhew himſelfe acceptable and thankeful vnto God for thoſe his ſo many and ineſtimable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits towards vs in his only begotten Son
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2309:52"/>Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>This we ſhall performe, if wee come prepared vnto this ſpiritual repaſt and banquet, having about vs our wedding robes: as faith, repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, loue vnfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thankfulnes, &amp;c. ſeeing indeede that the Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelicall wedding garment, (ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by our Saviour himſelfe, <hi>Mat,</hi> 22 <hi>cap,</hi> 10, 11, 12, <hi>ver.</hi>) is principally deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bewtified with theſe, that is to ſay, with faith and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The vſuall formes &amp; names of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is called ſometime <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſometime <hi>ſcutum fidei,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, truſt, boldnes, ſtrength, ſhield of faith, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<note place="margin">Eph. 6. c. 10. 16. v. Eph. 3.12. Hebr. 10.21.22. 1 Ioh 3.19.20.21. 1 Ioh 4 17. 2. Ioh 5.14.</note> full aſſurance: which the <hi>Latins</hi> expreſſe fitly by <hi>fiducia</hi> &amp; it doth direct ly anſwere vnto the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which is a Metaphore drawen from veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels or ſhippes vpon the ſea, that when they once haue their iuſt fraught, charg and lading it is after ſtill caried <hi>cum ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis velis,</hi> that is to ſay, more evenly and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2309:52"/>ſleddily then before it was, being emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſemblabelie our faith whilſt it is yet weake and little, or greene in the blade as they ſay, it may be compared in ſorte with an emptie veſſell; which after it hath growen vp in degrees and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from faith to faith, vntill it comes <hi>ad</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ipſam,</hi> that is, to her iuſt and even waight: it after hoiſſeth it ſelfe vp <hi>cum plenis velis</hi> with ful ſailes, &amp; cutteth her way along moſt ſtedily, throughout all the dangerous ſyrtes &amp; gulſes of this ſwelling and raging world, without (<hi>Iac.</hi> 1.6.) anie farther ſcruple,
<note n="*" place="margin">The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts teach men to be alwaies doubtfull of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vation: ſurely a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, &amp; pelting po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. But vnleſſe it were ſo with theſe caterpillers of mens ſoules: how were it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that they ſhold picke vp ſo many pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as they do.</note> doubte, or wavering for the matter.</p>
            <p>The ſubiect or proper ſeate of which forenamed faith muſt be [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] the verie nobleſt part, the hart it ſelfe of man. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>verſe.</hi> And hence we may know the cauſe, why the Lord requireth it, and maketh ſo often menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof. As, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. <hi>My Sonne giue me thy heart.</hi> Beſides, ſee theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119, 1, 2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4, 29. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6, 5 6. 1, <hi>Sam.</hi> 16, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10, <hi>cap.</hi> 10, <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:2309:53"/>
            <p>In which faith of ours, before it takes deepe roote and ſo drawes neere vnto his ripenes; it doth in the meane vvhile ſome and ſome, as they ſaie, grow vp by three ſtemmes or kinds of motions, that is:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, <hi>Intellectus Cognitione</hi> by know ledge iſſuing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>vnderſtanding part</hi> of the Soule. But we may not reſt here onlie, for it is not enough to know: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is common to Diuels &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, aſwel as to our ſelues. <hi>The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels alſo beleeue it,</hi> (namelie that there is one God,) <hi>and tremble. Iac.</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondlie, <hi>voluntatis ſummo deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, ſtudio, &amp; aſſenſu</hi> by an earneſt deſire or longing, by a careful endevour &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting of the wil: and this onlie is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Elect alone, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2, <hi>cap.</hi> 13, <hi>verſe.</hi> Yea it is right worthelie ſpoken by the Spouſe <hi>Cant. Cantic.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.3. <hi>verſes,</hi> As. <hi>Therefore the Virgins loue thee. Draw me, we will runne after thee.</hi> Where note a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formity of the Spouſe the Church with Chriſt her huſbande,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2309:53"/>conſiſting in two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. An open and plaine confeſſion of her own weaknes and infirmitie, ſaying; <hi>trahe me, draw me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 A readines or willing minde &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of the Spirit, which ſaith; <hi>post te curremus</hi> we wil run after thee. Thus ſpeaketh S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn: <hi>No man can come to mee, except the Father, which hath ſent me, draw him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdlie, <hi>Plena tum demum cordis fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducia,</hi> which is that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker-like, a ſure, and vnremoueable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and ſetled perſwaſion in God through Chriſt: againſt which, the gates of <hi>Hell</hi> ſhal neuer bee able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, <hi>Math.</hi> 16, <hi>cap.</hi> 16, 17, 18, <hi>verſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Lastly, who muſt be excluded from this banquet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch, as are vnworthie therof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe therefore are <hi>vnworthie,</hi> that are without the couenant: as are Turks, Iewes perſiſting ſtill in obſtinacie. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts or the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned crew, as they tearm
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2309:54"/>themſelues, (when this ſect began, I thinke Hell was rakte for them:) to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Papiſts alſo as birds of a feather, <hi>(quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus inquam, Papiſtae, ſemper dum viuant malitioſi ac pertinaces,)</hi> though after an odde kind of ſort they belong vnto the viſible Church, may be added, to make vp the quaternitie of ſworne brothers in iniquitie.</p>
            <p>Beſides, Children at no hande maie come, becauſe they yet want iudgment to trie themſelues.</p>
            <p>Ideots alſo &amp; fanaticall people muſt be put by, becauſe they want the vſe of reaſon, to examine themſelues.</p>
            <p>But for hypocrits; the Miniſter ought not to exclude them as vnworthie: til it pleaſeth God to reueale their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; make it knowne. For which cauſe <hi>Iudas</hi> was admitted by Chriſt, vnto his Supper. For albeit his wickedneſſe was knowne well enough to the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: yet was it not notorious, and ſo knowne vnto men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Recapitulation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:2309:54"/>
            <p>Thus much ſo brieflie as I coulde of the three former general points, which I promiſed at the entrance of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, touching:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The iudgement of the Fathers for the right expoſition of the words of the inſtitution, <hi>This is my bodie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The autority of the holie Scriptures, the verie touchſtone and triall of trueth to confirme the ſame by manifolde and moſt manifeſt places.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The reaſons ſuch as the beſt writers do vſe to approue the ſame with the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities likewiſe, that doe follow in the contrarie ſenſe and taking of the words. Which if none can go downe nor make impreſſion into their heartes, it ſeemes that they are ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geably hard laced at the ſtomacke; &amp; I am ſorie withall to haue had ſo much to doe with them, as in the ende to looſe my labour: though I am glad and do ſtill reioice to haue ſpoken the truth, and no more then the truth.</p>
            <p>Nowe the fourth and laſt thing for which I am yet behinde with them, is,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2309:55"/>brieflie to vnſwathe vnto the view of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (that wil loath their ſhameleſſe ſhame,) euen this deteſtable impuritie, prophanenes, with the moſt odious and deformed monſter of their homeborne brat and inbred Romiſh Maſſe. And ſo in the ende vnrolling one little clue of their paralogiſing arguments &amp; craftie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veyances they vſe in ſmothering the matter and blearing the eies of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: whereof their Arch-leader <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> hath rolde vp whole bottomes in ſtore for them of riffe-raffe and all other <hi>ſircere-ſorcere:</hi> I wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude al by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto the Lord both to amend them and turne their hearts (if it bee his vvill) from theſe darke and muddie errors: &amp; alſo to defend vs from them, and from their wickedly intended complotments and whatſoeuer villanies els they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe ſtill againſt vs. Which do, O Lord, of thy great and vnſpeakable mercy, we beſeech thee in Chriſt Jeſus our onlie Saviour and redeemer.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:2309:55"/>
               <head>The fourth point concerning the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed confuſion and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in their Maſse.</head>
               <head type="sub">A right depicturation of the Popiſh Quinteſſenced Maſſe.</head>
               <p>HOw ſlylie the Papiſts deale vvith vs, and what turne-ſkinnes they are, iudge vvith your ſelfe. For now at an inſtant they doe audaciouſlie affirme a thing, vvhich in the turning of an hand they wil moſt retchleſlie deny.</p>
               <p>They do not <hi>kill</hi> (and they are men almoſt to bee credited) Chriſt in their Maſſe: no, vvhat then? Marrie forſooth they vſe him in a far more gentle ſorte, that is, they doe but ſacrifice him, they do no more in the vvide vvorld but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him, and offer him vp to God the Father. Surely a prettie diſh of birdes, and fit to bee ſerued in, to ſuch grout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heades as without a <hi>quare</hi> vvill beleeue it.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:2309:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecce ſacrificium hîc, ſed nullam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimam,</hi> that is, behold a ſacrifice, but no ſlaine ſacrifice. Theſe are ſhrewde horſons. Why theſe, I ſaie, make no bones at the matter to reduce how and vvhen they liſt a ſacrifice into his <hi>quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſsence,</hi> vvhich is to ordaine and make a phantaſtical, a conceipted, &amp; an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginatorie ſacrifice, that is, to leade it ſo far a field from his owne nature, that at the laſt it ſhal wholy leeſe it ſelfe, &amp; ſhal not haue ſo much as either matter or forme to be left in it. As this their Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſacrifice hath nor.</p>
               <p>For firſt thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or ſacrifices in the Levitical Law, vvhich vvere wholy burnt; the beaſts therof were ſlaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could be laide vpon the altar: and were not onlie bare <hi>ſacrificia,</hi> but alſo <hi>victimae</hi> too. Now theſe as types did prefigure to them Chriſt Ieſus both to bee ſlaine and ſo bee made a ſacrifice once for all. And as then thoſe typicall ſacrifices did conſiſt both of a viſible matter and forme: ſo did that true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2309:56"/>Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>For he was viſiblie putte to death by wicked men and his body nayled vnto the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>Now compare this true ſacrifice of Chriſt with that baſtardly one of the Maſſe: and ſee whether it wil hold ſtitch or noe. Surely the Maſſe is ſuch a rotten relique, that it cannot. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Chriſt was both a ſacrifice &amp; alſo a ſlaine ſacrifice, &amp; that no more then once, for the ſinnes of the world: In the Maſſe there is a ſacrifice, but they ſlay him not.</p>
               <p n="2">2 His was a propitiatorie ſacrifice <hi>once</hi> offered: but theirs (as they ſay) is a propitiatory one too, <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually</hi> offered.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Chriſts bodie hangd viſiblie vpon the croſſe: In the Maſſe it is <hi>inviſible,</hi> or to follow them cloſe at heeles by vſing their owne foppiſh tearmes, it is there <hi>miraculouſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let them know, that their faith which is builded alwaies thus on mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2309:57"/>cannot bee good nor paſſe for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in this place:</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it reſteth vpon an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſigne &amp; miracle done, neglecting the waightier matters which are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Sacramentes, as to beleeve [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] moſt aſſuredly the promiſes of God, (made vnto vs in his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus,) who is ever faithful and true and readie to performe on his behalfe: and therefore whoſoever doth apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them by a ſtedfaſt faith, he ſhal obteine them ſuer enough with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe of miracles: whereof they haue ſuch abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance, that they do even baske themſelves therein. ſee, 2, <hi>Theſsal,</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>ver. Math,</hi> 24. <hi>chap,</hi> 24. <hi>verſe. Revel,</hi> 13. <hi>cap,</hi> 13. <hi>v. Revel.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Signes &amp; eſpecially <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> are long ſince out of date, and haue no longer vſe among Chriſtians: &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were in vſe, they ſhewed forth the glorie of Chriſt, and likewiſe prepared a way vnto faith: but <hi>faith</hi> it ſelfe ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vp by <hi>hearing of the word,</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 10.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2309:57"/>
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi>) and by the ſame, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as here by the Supper chiefly, it is maintained, bred, nouriſhed, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if this Maſſie Miracle were true, then ſhould the body of Chriſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their tranſubſtantiated worke once done by the Prieſte, bee felt and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the ſenſes, that is, it might bee ſeene, handled, taſted: ſo that nowe the bread ſhould no more be the obiect of the ſenſes. This is proved by his like, <hi>Ioh</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.6: <hi>verſes,</hi> where Chriſt turned the water into wine, after which tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiation, the wine was percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the ſenſes, &amp; not the water anie more. Wherefore the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring of this true miracle of Chriſt with that of theirs, doth make the huge &amp; mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Maſsie</hi> miracle to appeare in his coulers, that is, to be a trim deviſe, coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and counterfeicte. But returne we to the compariſon:</p>
               <p n="4">4 And laſtly, Chriſts body on the Croſſe or elſewhere ſoever, was circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:2309:58"/>in place; For when he was in one place touching his body, hee was not at that inſtant in another, but Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the Maſſe is not circumſcribed in place; no, it is in many places at a nicke, nay, it is <hi>Vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> every where.</p>
               <p>Nowe behold heere <hi>punctatim</hi> the <hi>guinteſſenſed</hi> definition of this maſſie &amp; mouldie ſacrifice: viz.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a ſacrifice, &amp; yet no ſacrifice ſlaine, verie often and oftentimes, ſtill to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and continued, in viſible or miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe, incircumſcriptible, &amp; vbiquitarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tell me whether theſe are not ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers or no, to diſguize and turne a thing cleane out, as it were, into dublet and hoſe, in ſuch a mimical and painterlike manner as they doe. I graunt they may eaſily by ſnipping and clipping bring to paſſe what they will, ſeeing they haue al the tooles of incredible cunning &amp; craft to worke withall.</p>
               <p>Here let vs ſcan a little the 3. former branches of this quinteſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced ſacrifice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examination.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:2309:58"/>
               <p>Firſt it is a Sacrifice, I graunt, <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſticall;</hi> which is common to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whereof are diverſe kindes: as,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Of the lippes. <hi>Hoſe,</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 3 <hi>ver. Hebr.</hi> 13.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Of the hart and ſpirit <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.16.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Of the whole body. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet are Baptiſme &amp; the Supper prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie ordeyned by Chriſt himſelfe to be <hi>Sacraments,</hi> though in reſpect of our own ſelues they are <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> by which we doe ſhew our obedience and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falnes to God, for the incomparable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of our redemption wrought by Chriſt, in offering vp his body for vs vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſſe once for all.</p>
               <p>Nay, (ſay they,) it is a propitiatorie ſacrifice, or elſe twil not ſerve our turne.</p>
               <p>I ſee one had need of a ladle or a long ſpoone at leaſt, that wil eate out of the devils diſh. There is no ſtriving at all with theſe coaps-mates: as good giue it them, for they wil haue it by hooke or by crooke.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:2309:59"/>
               <p>But aske them a reaſon, why? they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere at firſt daſh from the inſtitution, <hi>Hoc facite doc this,</hi> that is, (as they dreame,) <hi>conſecrate, offerte, ſacrificato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> conſecrate, offer, ſacrifice &amp;c. The vſe of which word <hi>[facio]</hi> put for <hi>ſacrifico</hi> for want of ſcripture, they are driven to a miſerable exige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to produce no worſe auctor then a Poet: <hi>Cum faciam vitulos pro frugibus &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>cum ſacrificabo.</hi> Well let this ſlide.</p>
               <p>Aske them againe, why they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not to alleadge that, which they were to haue done by ſpecial comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of our Saviour, that is, in <hi>reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of him.</p>
               <p>If they ſay that they do it for a <hi>reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of him; then whie doe they alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and improper thus the words from their owne ſignification and nature, as in ſteede of <hi>doe this</hi> plainely and ſimplie according to Chriſts way: they muſt needes haue it their owne waie, or elſe it ſhal lye to doing for them, and that is, <hi>conſecrate, offer, ſacrifice</hi> it. For by theſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2309:59"/>words, ſay they, Chriſt <hi>ordered</hi> his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and made them Prieſtes, to doe as he did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Confutation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt this falſe doctrine, we reade very ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes that Chriſt was but once offered and that vpon the Croſse,</hi> which was wholy &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſufficient by it ſelfe, to wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes of all that doe beleeve in him. Yet theſe Tinker-budghets come in and ſay, that Chriſt did, ſitting at his laſt ſupper, even before his Paſſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate and offer himſelfe vp a ſacrifice, which muſt then be twiſe. What? do ye marveile ſo much at this, ſay they again? whie, wee our ſelues bluſhe not to offer him vp an whole million of times at the leaſt. Furthermore theſe choppers, (to ſette a better face vpon the matter then they haue ſound hearts in the matter) devide the ſupper into two actions, the firſt and the laſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The firſt; <hi>Take, eate, this is my body, vvhich is given for you: take, drinke yee,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2309:60"/>this Cup is the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in my blood, vvhich is ſhed for you:</hi> this belongeth to all both Prieſte and people, yet they lie toe by their leaue, for they depriue the Laitie of the Cuppe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſecond; <hi>do this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of mee,</hi> pertaineth to the Prieſt alone.</p>
               <p>O what horrible and moſt abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble renting and mangling of the Lords Supper is this? Iudge with your ſelves, whether this bee to ſhewe the Lordes death till he come: or elſe, whether it be not rather to ſeeke his death, and to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie him anewe.</p>
               <p>For that, in memorial whereof we do any thing, is not it ſelfe <hi>preſent,</hi> becauſe wee are not ſaide to remember thinges that are <hi>preſent.</hi> But to <hi>doe this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him,</hi> is, when we thinking and meditating on his benefits, which hee hath done for vs, and which are by theſe rites recalled into our memorie: and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when we verely feeling &amp; finding in hart, that hee hath given vs theſe his benefits: doe celebrate them by publike
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2309:60"/>confeſſion before God, and Angels, yea before men alſo, and ſo doe giue thankes for them. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſumme of theſe wordes, is:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Faith</hi> in our hartes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> ioyned with a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique confeſſion of him.</p>
               <p>By this it is manifeſt ynough, howe theſe words heere are to be taken, ſeing that Chriſt ſaid not; <hi>doe this</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vpon my preſence,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vpon my remembrance,</hi> or in recalling of me into your minde and memorie by a ſtrong and lively faith. As if hee ſhould ſaye; there is no cauſe of thinking on the bodily preſence of mee in the bread &amp; wine of the Supper: nay, there is great cauſe rather of alienating your mindes away from that terrene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration vnto heavenly matters by the vertue of my remembrance. In to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken whereof they vſed of old to ſay: <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum corda habemus ad Dominum,</hi> that is, we lift vp our hartes vnto the Lord.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, theſe dreamers &amp;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2309:61"/>long experienced fable-tellers, referre this to none but to their Prieſtes, who are their onely ſticklers of the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tranſubſtantiation.</p>
               <p>In which looke, I pray, how profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they vſe, nay abuſe the wordes of the inſtitution as; for <hi>this is my bodie:</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>this is my bloode:</hi> which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce &amp; vtter over the bread &amp; wine, that the breath of their owne mouthes togither with the ſigne of the Croſſe, may touch the bread and the Cuppe, to the end, that by vertue therof they may bee tranſubſtantiated into the body and blood of the Lord: after which there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth but onely the bare accidentes of bread &amp; wine, as likenes, roundenes, whitenes, thinnes, moyſtnes and couler of wine.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiated</hi> body now made and faſhioned by the Prieſt, taken and eaten of them, deſcendeth carnally into their body, remaineth as long in their bellies, as the formes themſelues of bread and wine remaine. Aſke what
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2309:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>becomes of it afterward: theſe <hi>Owlards</hi> are at a <hi>non-plus</hi> euen at their wits ende about it, and cannot tel.</p>
               <p>Here ye ſee the braue ſkil of the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Prieſt, how workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly he contriues his matters, ye ſee againe his <hi>Ordering</hi> (ſuch as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinke vp) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the words, <hi>doe this;</hi> that is, conſecrate, trranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate, <hi>offer</hi> Chriſt: when as yet Chriſt ſaith not, <hi>Hoc offerte Deo patri offer this to God the Father:</hi> but <hi>Hoc facite, do this.</hi> For he had not as yet offered at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his body and blood, but he was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboute to offer it on the croſſe: Wherefore hee biddeth not that they ſhoulde offer, but that which hee had done at the table, euen that thinge they ſhould doe themſelues likewiſe. That which hee was about to doe vpon the croſſe, he was to doe it himſelfe alone: but that he had done at the table, hee would it ſhould rather be our work, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne.</p>
               <p>And this he had done to the ende he mighte ordaine this rite of breaking
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2309:62"/>bread, &amp; might commend the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Church, to be kept and celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>Thus we haue heard why the Maſſe is a <hi>propitiatorie ſacrifice, pro vivis &amp; mortuis,</hi> with their reaſons; I wil helpe them to one more my ſelfe, &amp; it is this: ſeeing the neceſſity of their prowde v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping catholike Romiſh church doth claime and require it to be ſo. Becauſe indeede the Maſſe and Purgatory vault (which depends thereon) are the Popes two dearling daughters of wealth moſt deteſtablie, vildly, iugglingly, &amp; cunny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catchingly gotten vnder coulor therof. The exceſſiue gaines of which two arch toies and legerdemaines with other <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceries</hi> by long cuſtome, did heaue them vp into the height of pride, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures grew into extreame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and obloquie amongſt them: as I might inſtance from diuerſe voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly forwaxen (and one eſpeciallie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt, <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth) diabolical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belching Popes; whom partly for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2309:62"/>and partly for modeſty I diſdaine to nominate, leaſt percaſe, I ſhould defile the readers chaſt eares with their moſt lewd and ſtincking practiſes.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, as I ſaid ſo ſay I ſtil, take away the Popiſh Maſſe &amp; the Cabbins of Purgatory from them, and take away the two maine props of <hi>poperie:</hi> as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which ſpolkes, their cartwheele which turneth about ſo glibly in al duſk errours, patcheries, and ſuperſtitions, would ſoone quite cracke, and ſhiuer it ſelfe into a thouſand peeces. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſecond particle of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition.</head>
               <p>Aſke them againe about the ſecond branch, how they proue it to be <hi>ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, an <hi>vnſlaine,</hi> or <hi>bloodleſse ſacrifice:</hi> and ten to one, but they wil yeeld as wiſe and formal a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as they did before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The burnt ſacrifices could not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vpon the altar, vnleſſe they had
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2309:63"/>beene ſlaine or kild before &amp; they were ſuch neceſſarie and viciſſitudinary acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they could not bee perfect the one without the other: as for example, that which was offered vp for a burnt ſacrifice vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the altar, could not or had not bin in that forme and perſection of an oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnleſſe the beaſt it ſelfe were firſt of al killed: and likewiſe beeing kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it is not in the <hi>forme</hi> of a burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, vntil it be laide vpon the Altar and there conſumed.</p>
               <p>But our Sorboniſtical Papiſts do take that as they thinke wil ſerue their turne and they diſcarde the reſt: ſuppoſing thereby to ſtrike the marke, when as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe they marre their market by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A provident Papisticall dread.</head>
               <p>And this they do, as ouertaken with a certaine feare and terrour of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: leaſt that by ioining of both theſe actions, that is to ſay, by offering vp <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimam cruenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> a bloody ſacrifice, they might (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Heb 6.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2309:63"/>cap 6. verſe</hi>) <hi>crucifie</hi> againe vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the Sonne of God, and make a mocke of him. Neuertheleſſe, albeit they burſt in two, for verie madnes and furie: yet are they not able to rid their hands, nor cleare their ſeared &amp; gawled conſciences hereof.</p>
               <p>For Chriſt Ieſus as he died but once, ſo was hee offered no more then once. Theſe two are inſeparable things of his Paſſion: as,</p>
               <p n="1">1 The ſhedding of his blood by which he vvas made that ſame (<hi>victima cruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta) bloody ſacrifice</hi> for vs, &amp; that but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie once neither: as for that (<hi>victima</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>bloodleſſe ſacrifice,</hi> he neuer was ſuch, and the whole courſe of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doth gaine-ſay it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The offering vp of his bodie vpon the croſſe, which was alſo done no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once. Now what reaſon have the Papiſts thus to diſſeuer and ſeparate theſe two, which may not nor cannot anie kinde of way be ſeuered. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing they are ſo hot vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpur,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2309:64"/>that they wil (whoſoeuer ſaith nay) haue Chriſt to bee often offered: then muſt they euen ſpight of their noſe haue him in like manner to be often ſlaine too.</p>
               <p>Let them not thinke to turne it over their thumbs thus childiſhſlie, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that their ſacrifice in the Maſſe is <hi>incruenta,</hi> an vnkilde or vnbloody ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: no ſurelie this forged invention of theirs is by manie pounds to light in the ballance, and being compared with the truth, wilbe returned home vnto them for want of waight.</p>
               <p>To conclude, the offering vp the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood of Chriſt is ſo done, that being perfected once vpon the croſſe, it may not be done againe. For Chriſt by once offering himſelfe died and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and it cannot be, that he ſhould after that die againe. Neither can it be <hi>victima Chriſti;</hi> the ſacrifice of Chriſt for remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins, which is (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) without blood. Touching which thing read the ninth Chapter to the Hebrews &amp; there you ſhal finde that this blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2309:64"/>ſacrifice in the Maſſe is nothing els but a <hi>Mockerie</hi> of the true and perfect ſacrifice of Chriſt, which was with bloode.</p>
               <p>And queſtionles, the oblation and death of Chriſt are ſo combined &amp; knit togither that it is impoſſible for the one truly to be perfected without the other. Wherfore whoſoeuer goe about to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Chriſt againe, &amp; that too for remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, do attempt alſo after the ſame manner to <hi>crucifice him anew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This vndoubtedly many do, crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>to themſelues</hi> the ſon of God: when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as yet no man is once able to <hi>crucifie</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine Chriſt himſelfe <hi>in ſe,</hi> that is, <hi>in himſelfe:</hi> and therefore can neither of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him.</p>
               <p>And from hence it is, that <hi>with one only oblation he hath made perfect or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated for ever them that are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Heb.</hi> 10.14. Becauſe the offering vp of himſelfe did require ſuch a death of his, as was perfuſed with blood: which death was only once; <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.10. and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2309:65"/>therefore muſt his oblation be no more then only (<hi>Heb.</hi> 7.27.) once. Becauſe, looke how manie <hi>oblations</hi> of Chriſt, ſo many <hi>deaths</hi> of neceſſity muſt there be. For theſe two can in no wiſe be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>That this is the truth, and no more then truth, Read <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.25.26.27.28. <hi>verſes.</hi> Leaue of then ye Papiſts thus to loue vanity &amp; to ſeeke after lies, as ye doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A third member of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition.</head>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly, after they haue in this faſhion made their Maſſe, to bee a propitiatorie ſacrifice, &amp; then a blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſacrifice, that is, not crucified or put to death by them: <hi>examine</hi> them againe why they doe <hi>continually offer</hi> him vpon their Alters, &amp; you ſhal heare them by and by anſwere you, wonderfull readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ridiculouſly.</p>
               <p>For what is this els, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they ſhould ſay; namely, that Chriſt himſelfe by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring vp himſelfe once for all, had done
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2309:65"/>nothing, or ſurely had ſcarſe done ynough: whereby it commeth to paſſe, (as wee ſee nowe in theſe Locuſtes of Rome, and frogges of the falſe Prophet, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.) that, that thing which Chriſt himſelf either could not o would not do, that (as experience teſtifieth to their open ſhame) theſe gallant ſhaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges by their Art more then magicall doe moſt graceleſſely &amp; ſacrilegiouſly endeavour to performe and finiſh.</p>
               <p>But theſe <hi>idle feakes,</hi> ſo they may keepe their vpper garments drie, make a light come off how much the water doth, in the meane while, ſwell aboue their ſhooes. For becauſe they will not in any caſe forſooth ſeeme tardie of kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; crucifying the Lord in their exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Maſſe, they wil vſe him in the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctableſt ſort, as their owne dreadſul and abominable hart can beſt imagin. Now how is that? even no more then a fewe times, (as a thouſand thouſand Millia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,) to offer him vp a ſacrifice vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars. Which vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the eaſieſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2309:66"/>amongſt ten thouſand to doe: but to vs it is as pleaſing, as daggers thruſt into our heartes.</p>
               <p>In the meane ſpace, they graunt as much as we requeſt, in ſaying; they doe but very oftentimes, often, that is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually offer vp Chriſt at their pleaſure by maſſing and remaſſing, by hoiſſing &amp; rehoiſſing, by da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dling of the hoſt, much after a rate, as children vſe to play with Puppets: which doth taſt ful and whole of the dregges of that ſpiritual fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whore of Babylon, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. wheras the ſcripture every where bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth flatte to the ground theſe &amp; al ſuch like droſſie, rotten, &amp; canker-eaten do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of mens owne brain-ſicke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. as ſee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 14, <hi>verſ. For with one offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hath hee conſecrated for ever them that are ſanctified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marke heere how the Apoſtle ſaith:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>One offering;</hi> there is no neede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of manie, often, or iterated offerings.</p>
               <p n="2">2 There is added <hi>He,</hi> who is that?
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2309:66"/>even none other, but Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="3">3 S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paule</hi> vſeth the word <hi>ever:</hi> to ſhew, that it is alwaies moſt powerful in it ſelfe, and effectual for ever.</p>
               <p>See the 12. ver. of the ſame chapter. And the whole 9. cap. reade it. Item <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. <hi>Chap.</hi> 27.28. <hi>verſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto of thoſe three former clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their <hi>quinteſsence-like</hi> extracted ſacrifice: yet one bone more for them to nibble vpon, and ſo an ende of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For one, (though wee ought not to bee wearie in well doing,) ſhal ſooner wearie himſelfe herein, then weary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſcruple of Conſcience vnto the Papistes.</head>
               <p>MOreover by offering vp of Chriſt an oblation or ſacrifice, what doe they but lift the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves aboue Chriſt. For the offerer is greater then his offering as were <hi>Abel, Abraham, Iacob, Iob,</hi> and others when they offered vp their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: ſo likewiſe the Prieſts, as <hi>Aaron</hi> &amp;
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2309:67"/>the reſt: &amp; ſo in like manner Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, conparing his <hi>divine nature</hi> with his <hi>humane body.</hi> But ſtay a while: what a contumely, I pray, is this againſt Chriſt thus inſolently and preſumptuouſlie to vaunt of their excellentnes before God to offer vp Chriſt his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: when as yet there is neither Angell, nor any creature may be found worthy, to enterpriſe or take this thing in hand. I could wiſh them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my hart, ſo much pietie or at leaſt humanitie, as to regard this well.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the Maſſe, as themſelves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme doth deſerve <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> that is, by the verie Maſſing of the Maſſe, (or threadbare vttering and huzzing of it,) not onely forgiuenes of ſinnes as touching men: but it meriteth alſo a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of cattle, oxen, hoggs, hens, geeſe and other deſeaſed beaſtes whatſoever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay what is there which this medcine of <hi>Daucus Maucus</hi> made, and (as I may ſo ſay) put out of his witts too by a prieſt, cannot worke vpon for money? It will
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2309:67"/>make, I marrie will it, the ſoules of al old beldams to whippe out of Purgatorie dungeon, and awaie amaine ſo faſt as a dogge may trotte, I know not whither my ſelf in al the world, nor they neither.</p>
               <p>To truſſe vp al in one fardle; theſe are thoſe verie miſhapen and more then hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous monſters of the Maſſe,
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> or bread worſhippe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>It muſt needes bee, that one and the ſame ſubſtance of the bodie of Chriſt hath diverſe formes, one which he tooke from the bleſſed virgin his mother: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther borrowed from the bakers ſhoppe, which theſe ſacrificulous chapmen by their ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne art of witchery haue pawnd al their creditt on, that they wil make fooles beleeve, it is his body. So then, there is one forme of him in the heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, another on the earth: one true &amp; beſett about with al proprieties and accidents, which after death aſcending he tooke a long with him, and tels vs that hee will come againe with the ſame vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2309:68"/>another imaginarie without any viſible ſhape and accidents obiect vnto our ſenſes, even that Miſſaticall one, which is neither in the bread, neither in the body, neither hangs it in the aire, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſticks it in the clammes of any ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficious hulkſter, neither doth it wabble downe into the ſtomacke: But it is that which is not, and is not that which it is: namely, verie that, it is ſuppoſed to be, which the diſtempered ſconces of dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticalizing Schoolemen by their often dreaminges haue ſhaped out, &amp; now (as they had done a long while ſince,) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude the ſame, becauſe it ſtands filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon their hands, vnto the dotardes of the world for a moſt abominable and monſtrous miracle.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>The</hi> 3. <hi>is a propitiatorie ſacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Sacraecoenae mutilatio deliibatio<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</hi> that is, A mangling or curtoling, an hacking or hewing, as one may tearme it, of the moſt holy <hi>Supper</hi> of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherfore this <hi>Maſse</hi> by the conſent
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2309:68"/>&amp; iudgment of the godly minded men, is to be condemned to the pitte of hell, becauſe it enfeebleth and maketh voide the ſtrength and vertue of that onely ſacriſice of Chriſt <hi>once offered:</hi> &amp; which is wholy and moſt abſolutely in it ſelfe, and by it ſelfe, and for it ſelfe availeable to wipe away all our ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A farewell to them.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Talem idcirco, vos Papistae, mangoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum foetum, &amp; fucum pluſquam diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum veſtrum, longiſsimè à nobis, quàm poſsitis, a pagitote. Chriſtum denig, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſemel cruciſixum, &amp; ſuper altare non niſi vna vice Deo patri pro nobis pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoribus ac miſellis oblatum, ab ſque om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni impostura, fraude, fuco, verè, ſincerè, ſemper<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> induite. Valete.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A right merrie and pleaſant Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix: dialogue wiſe.</head>
               <p>I determined to ſet downe a iuſt cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logg of vbiquitary ſophiſmes, ſleights and fallacies: but ſeeing I haue bin o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2309:69"/>alreadie, I wil herein vſe al poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible briefnes I can. By the way I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbeare to tel them, that they are in a miſerable and pitifull taking. For thus may ye thinke, how hardle the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt whetteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this bone, as it we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, of murmuring, ſpight, and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed malice againſt vs, faying oh where are thoſe daies of old become, wherein wee eate, dranke, ſlept our bellies ſul, when our neckes grew in ſtrength, &amp; our eies could ſcarce peepe out for fatnes, when we laught &amp; were right iocandary, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing our ſelues in delights, ſporting our ſelues in witty tales of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dominike, Fraunces, Cutberd, Becket,</hi> and ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquious men of ours, whenas we enhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored our ſelues in moſt vitious ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie within the cloyſters &amp; monaſteries, and did let the world wagge: whenas we heard but little of theſe Scripture mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, neither was there one amongſt an hundred of vs before <hi>Luthers</hi> daies which troubled himſelfe herein, the law was ſo brauelie on our ſides, that we did
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2309:69"/>euen what we liſt, &amp; had alſo what hart could wiſh, nay if we did no more but buzze in the peoples eares, that <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was the mother of pure devotion,</hi> it vvas taken ſtraight for an <hi>axiome</hi> and ground of Doctrine. Here ye may think againe how this woful Papiſt doth fetch me vp an inlie ſigh, and ſaies; oh vvhat a change is this from the better vnto the vvorſe? What a promotion vnto our fraternitie &amp; order, out of the hall to be popt into the kitchin, or els, out of Gods bleſſing, as the proverbe is, to come forthwith into a vvarme ſunne? Vpon this the Papiſt not vviſhing vvhich way to turne his head ſo adled with lunatik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and reſtleſſe griefe, fals me inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentlie into a prepoſterous courſe of ex clamation and downe-right rauing: <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Luther, Luther</hi> that euer thou waſt borne, thus to haue reclaimde our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines &amp; diſclaimde our doings; thou, thou vvhich vvaſt one of our conſorte, packe, &amp; crew, haſt ſpoild our market, Indulgences do ſtand vpon our hands,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2309:70"/>our <hi>Maſſes</hi> are derided, the ſecond <hi>vault</hi> of <hi>Hell</hi> vvhich is our Purgatorie is reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned no otherwiſe then a tale of <hi>Robin Hoode,</hi> our Pilgrimages &amp; guilded ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies are entituled by no better name then Popiſh bables, our ſuperſtitious ceremonies which coſt much good hot liquor &amp; many a draught of warme ale for the inuention of them, are thruſt by into corners as rags of carnal rites and plaine hypocriſie, there is no more roome left for reliques, yea which is more and the greateſt plague vnto vs, euen all goeth downe, al goeth out, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing goeth in, our yron bonded &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hutches are welneere for the moſt part coineleſſe, hollow, void, &amp; empty. At length this exclamation ended, the Papiſt better bethinking himſelfe, by turning his tale cleane rounde deviſeth withall how to helpe &amp; rub out in theſe his paſſing-ſorrowfull and miſdeeming haps. And therefore as one ſeeking a new laſt to beate his ſhoo vpon after that the olde can ſerue his turne no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2309:70"/>hee beginneth thus to excogitate a way which ſhal not any thing meanely, as he thinks, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him inſteed. Wel, ſaith he, vnto his brother Papiſt, ſeeing this matter will cotten no better in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, we muſt learn to turne the ſtream ſome other way. <hi>Blindnes</hi> and <hi>ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> are chaſed away, the maine pillers of our building: and therefore if wee will keepe vp ſtill the houſe ouer our eares that it fal not down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, it behooves vs mightely to vnderſet it with our <hi>cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Cunning,</hi> quoth the other, alas for woe; our cauſe is ſo paſſing bad, that if we appeale vnto theſe latter reformed yeares, al men for the moſt part cry out and ſay, fie vpon it: if vnto the Fathers, they alſo on the other ſide are too hard iudges againſt vs. Tuſh, Brother quoth hee againe, let mee tugge and trie with the Fathers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, the Fathers are reade but of few, <note place="margin">The Index expurgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius would be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned here.</note> and thoſe which read them do not read them all: therfore it is a ſmal thing with me to belie the Fathers.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:2309:71"/>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, the Fathers were but men as we are, &amp; therefore did ſomtime ſlip; now my purpoſe is, <hi>vt volute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceribus Patrum, id eſt, in eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>erroribus:</hi> and it ſhall ſcape me hard but I wil find them where they lie. Yea but this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevaile, quoth the other, whiles the Scriptures are ſo ſtrong againſt vs. Thou art a foole Brother, ſaid the other, and knoweſt not howe to beſtirre thy ſtumpes handſomely in theſe matters: I that am an old fox and beaten herein, can with great eaſe wreſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to what ſenſe I will my ſelfe. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheles, quoth the other, this knauery of thine will ſoone bee ſpied by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the place. Though it bee ſaith the other, yet haue I moe yrons in the fire at once then one, to helpe at a pintch &amp; time of neede: which is to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate &amp; infold the plaine truth in obſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie of words of art, after the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of the <hi>Dunces;</hi> in which knackes <hi>Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard, Aquinas, Scotus, Gabriel Biel</hi> &amp;c. will furniſh me with avoidances at ſuch
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2309:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>deade liftes.</p>
               <p>Yea; I tell thee Brother, it will do me ſuch an odlie pleaſure, that I ſhal not need to feare how rightly in I am or elſe howe widely out: and ſeeing I know not where I am my ſelfe either in right or wrong, (yet cocke ſure ynough in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extricable labarinth of Sorbonizing ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes:) others thou maieſt iudge with thy ſelfe, muſt needs haue picking meate for ſome prety ſturte to finde it out.</p>
               <p>Graunt it to bee as thou haſt ſaide, quoth the other, thou canſt not ſhifte thy handes for all this wylie-pylienes of thine, from thoſe <hi>Lutherans</hi> and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: but they will winde thee out of thy intricableſt doublings of deceavea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubtleties and guiles; which beeing done, thou haſt no more then out of the land the ditch, that is, thy naked traveile for thy paine: and beſides, thou art as farre of ſtill from the ayme thou ſhot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt at, as thou waſt at the firſt onſett, when thou ſo meagerly beganſt to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:2309:72"/>it.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe Brother, ſaide he againe, that thy wordes doe beare ſome palme with them, yet ſuch is our caſe and it is to be lamented, that, vnleſſe we did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hammer our heades and quiddifie our wits as it were vnto the proofe herein, our kingdome had gone longe ſince wholy vnto potte. And what marveile, being ſo deadly windſhaken at the hart &amp; tottering too, as it is: that did we not take horrible heede therevnto, it would ſuddainly fall into a ſound, by ſincking into the duſt of vtter ruin &amp; deſolation.</p>
               <p>It is a ſaying, that a ſcald mans head is quicklie broken; then how ought wee to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in bodely feare of our Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian head the Pope, who hath not, as theſe <hi>Lutherans</hi> hold &amp; Proteſtants to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, ſo much as an heares breadth of hoalenes in it: leſt through our negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence &amp; want of ſeeing therto, it might not onely be broken (for ſo it is already to our great diſcomfortes,) but alſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and quaſht to peeces. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2309:72"/>in my bare iudgement, brother Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, we are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully ſuſtained by that matchles Iewel of our Popiſh Church, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> by name; that were it not ſo, that we enioyed his paineful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying traveiles: it could not be choſen, but we ſhould haue bin left to lie in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ditch long before.</p>
               <p>I doe gladly ſubſcribe, quoth the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vnto your graue and learned ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit: but yet not ſo, as fully ſatiſfied. For <hi>Bellarmine</hi> indeede hath gone far here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and we may not ſee abroad without his ſpectacles: but I tell you this by the waie, &amp; it tendeth not a little to our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance, if not vndoing; that whereas <hi>Bellarmine</hi> was wont to bee appropried vnto our ſelues, he is now made an atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in common ſtudies? and what ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? of our owne men generally, trow you? Noe ſurelie our owne adverſaries. Whie, thy are ſo well experienced in him, that we can no ſooner filch an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and open our mouthes to vrge it: but they knowe from what Inne hee
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:2309:73"/>came, they haue him by the top by and by, and will hardly afford vs ſo much breath as to ſpet him forth, before they will haue fairely and roundly anſwered it. Beſides if this were all, that this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe did ſpread no further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſome fewe of vs of thinferiour route, (though we would leaſt haue it ſo by our willes,) it might goe wel: but they wade deeper and deeper ſtil, never leaving till they feele the bottome, &amp; having grounded once, they do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſhoulderſhake our chieffeſt forgeman, the good old man &amp; father M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Robin Bellarmine</hi> (a <hi>Card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naule</hi> too I weene,) by toſſing and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, by volving and revolving of his leaves, (which by many mens ſweate he hammerd vp,) that he hardly gettes a quiet nights reſt for them.</p>
               <p>And learne; I pray what a compe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous method they begin to take with him; For when he is in hand to treate of verie weightie matters, (as thinke it to be either Praiers for the dead, Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the bleſſed Virgin, by ſaying to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:2309:73"/>her, <hi>Rogapatrem, iube natum, &amp; iure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris impera,</hi> or elſe vpon other holie Saints; likewiſe when hee handleth the point of Satisfaction to bee done by vs or by other after our deaths for vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he decideth the foundation and recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle of ſatisfactions, even that verie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Purgatory blindhouſe of ours, <hi>Helle</hi> firſt cowſen, againe when he falleth (by breaking his owne necke) into the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundity and depth of that grande que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, touching the ſcriptures &amp; the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of our church aboue the ſame, &amp; of the ſupremacie of our mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrouſe Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raganticall head the Popes owne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes himſelfe, (with other deciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of no leſſe valewe:) and hath ſpoken and blat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd out ſo much vpon everie one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularlie, as might ſeeme to fill an houſe: what do theſe younkers then, but croſſe over a neerer way to woode, and doe by and by reduce mee all which hee hath ſcratcht &amp; rapt togither (by other folkes drudgerie) ſo laboriouſly, into a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold claſſe and order: as,</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:2309:74"/>
               <p n="1">1 Into the iudgment of the Fathers, and orthodoxal councels.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Into the waight &amp; force of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Into the thing which preſſeth moſt &amp; ſtriketh deade as they ſaie; that is, the auctoritie of the holie Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> touching either fathers or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, if they agree with the word of God, they embrace and reverence their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: but if they once ſquare and differ, they let them lie dead vpon <hi>Bellarmines</hi> owne hand to make the beſt of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> they yeelde that his reaſons are ſomewhat acute, ſharpe, &amp; keene: but ſhrewdly peſtered with ſophiſticall concluſions, which they in downe right Engliſh cal deceiptful fallacies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> when he commeth vnto the word it ſelfe, being the ſureſt &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt weapon he hath againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: why there, ſaie they, hee ſtriketh the fainteſt blowe. For the places which hee bringeth are both farre fette, and ſmell verie hoatlie in their noſes of the <hi>wreaſt.</hi> And this is
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:2309:74"/>their vſe and guiſe in everie thing, that nothing now a daies doth paſſe vnſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vewed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which cauſeth me a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times at leaſt, to wiſh for blindnes and palpable ignorance, to circumfuſe and overſpredd againe the earth, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely pearles of price, that are by many degrees for our wealth and ſtore, to bee preferred before this cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning captiouſnes. For in elder time men every where poſſeſt with blinde devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; drinking out of the cup of errours and ſuperſtitions, ſuckt in many a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie flie, which yet they found no faulte withal: but ſince this captious cavillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ours ſtarted vp, we are never out of worke, our Adverſaries do ſo fire our breeches, and foxe vs backe ſo eagerlie vnto the earth of ſubtile inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions, that we puffe and blow about it, &amp; as it were melt our ſelues away in our greaſe, not having an <hi>Alphabet while</hi> ſo much as to peere out a little our heades and fetch breath for them.</p>
               <p>Moreover, when we haue laboured
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:2309:75"/>in our celles as men for life &amp; death, &amp; our laboures chaunce to light into their fiſtes: they doe ſo file and refile over and over our hammer beaten ſtuffe, that in the end it goes wel with vs, if there bee found the leaſt glimmering ſhine of truth in it.</p>
               <p>In the mean time I deny not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but that this is beneficial vnto our Papal &amp; Pontificious orders, &amp; a great deale more I ſuppoſe it would be, were al comparable in theſe feates vnto thy ſelfe: but there are ſuch a rabble of <hi>biffe boffe</hi> Papiſtes, idiotical &amp; ſimple; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am one (without ſhame bee it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,) my ſelfe: that if any be ſawcie with with vs to vnderſtand our reaſons, wee do no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet this Stand a broach, which is; <hi>The holie Catholike Mother Church of Rome hath thus determined it: &amp; therfore (talke no more,) of neceſsitie it muſt bee ſo.</hi> And if they vrge vs any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no way then is lefte for vs but one, namely, to ruſh into the multitude of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſts, which are called <hi>omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſimpliciſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:2309:75"/>&amp; stolidiſsimi,</hi> that is, dreaming and welmeaning Papiſts though they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not nor will not expreſſe it, &amp; ſay with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>It is my conſcience,</hi> which (I thinke) a bare ioynd ſtoole, had it the vſe of ſpeech, would ſay as much or more.</p>
               <p>Norwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, though I thus come ſhorte of thee in intricable ſophiſticati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet do I beare as great good wil vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that game as thou doſt for thy guts; and doe deſire that I had but a quarter of thy excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t skil herein, thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perceiue that I would briſtle after an other manner of ſort, then yet I do, with theſe ordinarie prying Proteſtants into our doings: but I fear me theſe <hi>Elenches</hi> are ſo abſtruſe &amp; hard, as they wil never whilſt the world ſtands, enter within my clockhouſe of conceipte, to conſider of them.</p>
               <p>Well Brother, quoth the other, I haue hitherto with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; willingly heard thy tale, becauſe I ſee thy willingneſſe great to vie with mee, though thine abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is but ſmale.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:2309:76"/>
               <p>Concerning thoſe afterfetches and recanvaſſing of our doeings by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes, thou haſt hitte the naile right vpon the head, in ſo ſenſiblie portraiting them out before me. Wherfore as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan this fraternal communication with thee, ſo do I conclude the ſame; that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are thus extreamely firkt, beſert, vext, and counterchardged by our eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: we muſt neceſſarily like true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, (if wee intend to vphold the glittering pride of our Mother Church at Rome,) toile night &amp; daie like packe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſes, &amp; take intollerable paines, aſwel directlie in ſmothering of the truth, by wreaſting (<hi>Loc. Com. Muſc.</hi> 161.) the right ſenſe of it cleane camme from the drifte and purpoſe of the writer: as alſo indirectly, what we can, in reobſcuring the ſame with doubte vpon doubte by our ſcholaſtical and queſtionizing alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, foraſmuch as thou haſt made knowen vnto me thy ſtudiouſe minde to congratifie with mee and the reſt of our
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:2309:76"/>ſocietie, the catholike mother Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> and our holy Papal Father of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Angelo</hi> in Rome, (who is the head therof, as thou knoweſt wel ynough,) in ſuch like manner knowledge of depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and inverting the Scriptures &amp; in falſly ſyllogizing therevpon: heere is my hand, vſe me anie night thou wilt, &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe, I wil both indoctorate and Papiſtifie thee with that ſuperexcellent qualitie, as alſo for thy fidelity vnto my ſelfe, and for thy true hearted Catholik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto the Church, will performe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee anie other good elſe what I can. And thus, my Brother Papiſt, I bidd thee, till our nexte meeting in ſome ſuch like blacke darckeſome miſtie rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten weather, hartelie adewe.</p>
               <p>I haue purpoſely vſed prolixity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I could no way better then vvith ſome delight both laugh at their wilfull ſelfe-pleaſing allurements vnto folly, &amp; ekewiſe diſplay the accuſtomed dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable pranks of al ſuperſtitiouſly ſworn and vnreturnable vowed Papiſtes.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:2309:77"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two or three, at last, Vbiquitary argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſo an end.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vbiquities of the true naturall bodie of Chriſt.</head>
               <p n="1">1 The body of Chriſt is inuiſible: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath the <hi>grace</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, of <hi>diſpenſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Confutation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay that is falſe; becauſe, that the body of Chriſt is not by <hi>nature</hi> inviſible no not after his reſurrection, as, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.28.29. <hi>verſes. Luk.</hi> 24. <hi>cap.</hi> 39. <hi>v.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>Vbiquitaries</hi> doe moſt groſlie forge a new ſignification of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or diſpenſation: which for ſooth very trimly they vſe for the feigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned maieſtie of the fleſh of Chriſt, that is, for the <hi>vbiquitie</hi> of it, when notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Fathers haue called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>or diſpenſation,</hi> euen the <hi>whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation</hi> and <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt by taking of fleſh. <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Dial.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The <hi>Vbiquitaries</hi> for the true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:2309:77"/>
                  <hi>[idiomatum]</hi> of the propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties of both natures of Chriſt into one <hi>Perſon,</hi> wil by and by haue ſignified vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this forme of ſpeech <hi>proprietatum tranfuſionem;</hi> that is, a tranſfuſion of Proprieties out of one nature of Chriſt into an other, as may bee out of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine into his humane nature: ſo that they wil haue the Proprieties of his Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or godhead to be <hi>communicated</hi> vnto his <hi>Humanitie.</hi> But this axiome is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; overthrowes it ſelfe. For if once they be <hi>proprieties</hi> then are they not <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated:</hi> and if they bee <hi>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> then are they not <hi>proprieties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 The like quaint and paſſing euil im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper ſpeech before this neuer hearde of haue they counterfeited in theſe two voices, <hi>Abſtract and Concret:</hi> teaching that the humane nature of Chriſt is not every where in the <hi>Abſtract,</hi> that is, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted and ſeparated from his diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but it is euery where in the <hi>Concret,</hi> that is, concreted and vnited vnto the <hi>Deity.</hi> Is not this, I pray, trecherouſly to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:2309:78"/>corrupte the vſuall ſpeaking of the church? They know I am ſure that an <hi>Abſtract</hi> is the name of a <hi>nature</hi> or <hi>form</hi> whatſoeuer, which is in ſome other ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>eſſentially</hi> or <hi>accidentally,</hi> as are theſe; <hi>deitie, Humanitie, VViſdome, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> but the <hi>Concret</hi> doth ſignifie the <hi>thing it ſelfe</hi> or the <hi>Subiect,</hi> which hath that nature and forme, as; <hi>God, Man, VViſe, Iuſt.</hi> Now how true this is, which they goe about, al men know right well. For the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cret</hi> of Chriſts diuine nature is to be God himſelfe: the <hi>abſtract</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is his <hi>Deitie.</hi> Likewiſe the <hi>Concret</hi> of his humane nature is to be <hi>Man:</hi> &amp; the <hi>Abſtract</hi> hereof is his <hi>Humanity.</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe tearmes of Art, according as they wil haue them, and it is al one, as if they had ſaid: that the humane nature of Chriſt is every where, as hee is <hi>Man,</hi> which is the <hi>Concret:</hi> but he is not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in his <hi>Humanity,</hi> which is the <hi>Abſtract.</hi> Iudge whether this bee not workemanlie knockt and beaten out by their <hi>ſophistrizing</hi> hammer.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:2309:78"/>
               <p n="4">4 Fourthly, and laſtly; the <hi>vbiquitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> trifle moſt paſſing idlely in behat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching a threefold ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of the body of Chriſt: that is,
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>A naturall manner.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>A glorious manner.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>A maiesticall manner.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt two waies, they denie mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veylous crookedly that Chriſt is euerie where in body: but come ye once to the thirde, which is his <hi>manner of Maieſty;</hi> then haue, ſay they, along with you to Weſtminſter, ſeeing in this ſort both there and euery where els throughout the world, we ſhal neuer miſſe him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt here is in this diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Catachreſis or abuſe of the voice, <hi>manner,</hi> which is placed heere moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly for an <hi>adiunct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the parts do not cohere &amp; agree with the <hi>Diſtribute:</hi> for the <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner</hi> is not an Adiunct of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, but it is the <hi>forme it ſelfe.</hi> And as for that their <hi>manner of Maieſty,</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:2309:79"/>ſome men are over haſtie to tearme it, <hi>figmentum perquiſitè excogitatum:</hi> but I had rather ſpeake Engliſh, and call it a plaine <hi>cogge</hi> and foiſted <hi>legerdemaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Partes do not oppoſitlie diſagree betwixt themſelues; becauſe the glorie of the natural body is an <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunct,</hi> and it remaineth, (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the adiunct) ſtil a true phyſical &amp; natural body, although it be alſo glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For <hi>glorificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> hath not taken away the <hi>nature</hi> of Chriſt his body, but the <hi>infirmitie</hi> thereof &amp; <hi>patibilitie.</hi> But theſe <hi>Vbiquitaries</hi> are ſure cardes, take them at any time without a <hi>fitten,</hi> and ſtrike of their neckes.</p>
               <p>They durſt not ſay that Chriſtes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural bodie is euerie where; fie, that were to groſſe: and therefore ſee what cunning can bring to paſſe; they haue wrought it out <hi>maiesticallie.</hi> Wherfore beholde their follie; whiles that they thinke to ſhun the raine, they run mee out of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d aboue head &amp; eares into the riuer. For it had bin as good, nay better
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:2309:79"/>for them to ſay at firſt daſh, that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural body of Chriſt is euerie where, &amp; ſo to make no more then one body of him: then by ſuch an vnartificial blinde diſtinction, both to affirme his body to be everie where, &amp; over and beſides to ordaine him a triple body too; that is, 1. a <hi>Naturall</hi> body: 2. a <hi>Glorious</hi> body: 3. a <hi>maiesticall</hi> bodie.</p>
               <p>I might ſet downe much more ſuch ſtuffe of theirs, but I count this ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſhew what they are, euen (in this reſpect) the Popes own ympes, and ſtill like vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; wil bee ſo, though the Diuel ſaie nay. This I doe, and maie ſpeake boldly, vpon regard of their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obſtinacie and malitious harts both againſt our ſelues, &amp; our doctrin. <hi>Ours?</hi> nay the Lords owne doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Corollarie and vpſhot of this whole treatiſe vpon the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>LEt vs moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeech the Lord our God of his abundant kindnes &amp; mercy towards vs in his Son Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:2309:80"/>that he wold ſtay vs with his grace, that we denying and defying from our harts al vngodlines, al hereſies, ſciſmes, erroneous opinions, falſe doctrines, all ſuperſtitious reliques &amp; ceremonies of that whoriſh church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in a word al <hi>Epicuriſme, Atheiſme, Papiſme, Bron niſme,</hi> we may be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the truth of his moſt powerful word, being nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed vp continuallie in a liuelie faith with this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly holy banquet, &amp; may perſiſt in ſtedfaſtnes of the ſame truth, even to our laſt breathing and yeelding vp the Ghoſt into the hands of our allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing &amp; gracious God, who hath faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie promiſed that hee will not faile vs nor forſake vs, (<hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5.) but wil bee readie then eſpeciallie by his holie An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to receaue vs vp vnto himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his holie mountaine and new Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, the citie (<hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.22.) of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God: where wee ſhall liue in ioyes vnvtterable with the congregation it ſelfe of the firſt borne, which are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heauen, &amp; with God the Iudge of al,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:2309:80"/>&amp; with the ſpirits of iuſt &amp; perfect men, And with Ieſus the Mediatour of the new Teſtament, and with the bloode of ſprinkeling, that ſpeaketh better things then that of Abell.</p>
               <p>God grant vs al theſe things for our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Ieſus ſake: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Father &amp; the holy Ghoſt be attributed al praiſe and glory now &amp; for ever. So be it. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Praier for the whole State of this Church and Realme of England, conteyning a true confeſsion of our ſinnes before the Lord: fitte to bee ſaide at all times and ſeaſons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Merciful Lord and Father, which refuſeſt not to hear thy ſervants at what time they doe flee vnto thee, in the contrition of their harts: we beſeech thee to expell the darkenes of our vnderſtanding, that being directed by thy holie Spirit we may, from a true
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:2309:81"/>feeling of our woeful ſtate, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt vnlocke our grieved co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, &amp; powre out the affections of our broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harts, by ſincerely invocating on thy holy &amp; bleſſed name, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Moſt gracious and louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee come vnto thee in the name of thy dearely beloued ſon Ieſus Chriſt, beſeeching thee out of the humility of our ſoules, that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vouchſafe to looke downe vpon vs with the eie of pittie, notwithſtanding moſt vile &amp; miſerable ſinners as we are; For we were conceaved in ſin &amp; borne in iniquitie, having no truth nor ſound part within vs, ſeeing from the ſole of the foote vnto the crowne of the head there is nothing whole but woundes &amp; ſwelling, &amp; ſoares ful of corruption: we are a ſeede of the wicked, corrupt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, forſaking the Lord and provoking the holie one of Iſrael to anger. Nowe though we are thus vncleane &amp; ſunken deepe into all impieties, though our
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:2309:81"/>righteouſnes be as filthy clouts, though we doe al fade like a leafe, and that our iniquities like the winde haue caried vs away; yet thou O Lord art mercie and truth, promiſing to harken vnto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſinners that doe cal vnto thee. We cal and crie vnto thee, O Lord, out of the true ſorrowes and grievances of our hearts to remove from vs the burden &amp; horrour of our ſinnes, which do lie moſt heavie vpon our conſciences, ſtinging and preſſing vs downe vnto the verie gates of Hell: thou therefore, ô heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, which ſaveſt both man and beaſt, thou whoſe mercie reacheth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heavens, and whoſe faithfulnes vnto the cloudes, thou whoſe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes is like the mightie mountaines, and thy iudgments like a great deepe, powre forth vpon vs (moſt ſillie wormes and vnworthie wretches as we are,) of the rich plentie of thy Grace, let thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed mercie breake forth and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent vs in al our actions, reforme our froward wils, our corrupt affections, our
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:2309:82"/>inbred depraved natures, create in vs cleane harts &amp; renue right Spirits with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs, that ſo our whole man both ſoules and bodies may bee conformed to thy holie will. And to this ende out of the longing deſires of our harts, we proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelues at the foote-ſtoole of thy mercie ſeate, doe craue of thee, ô boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Father, to quicken vs with thy holy Spirit; by whoſe gracious working, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freede from theſe helliſh downefals of ſin &amp; wickednes, of deſperate ſinnes, of preſumptuous ſinnes, of ſinnes by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, of ſinnes by commiſſion, of ſins by ignorance, of ſecrete ſinnes, of noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and outragious crying ſins, briefly of ſines againſt the firſt table, and of ſins againſt the ſecond table, we may the reſidue of our daies (which are but few and evill,) be lifted vp to place our cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations on heaven and heavenly things, there to contemplate with the eye of a ſtedfaſt and liuelie faith Chriſt Ieſus our alone and onely redeemer, that through a true feeling and apprehenſion therof,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:2309:82"/>wee may with that bleſſed Martyr S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Steven</hi> pearce the heavens and behould our alone al-ſufficient ſaving Mediatour ſtanding at the right hand of God, cladd with the garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of our ſleſh, both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the way and making interceſſion for vs: and that we likewiſe (by vertue of our myſtical incorporation and vnion with him,) receaving from his handes the garments of his righteouſnes, may be covered from the accuſations &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>For who is it that ſhal ſtand vp &amp; lay anie thing vnto our charge? It is God that iuſtifieth. Or who is it that ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne? It is Chriſt which is deade, yea or rather which is riſen againe, who is alſo at the right hand of God, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth requeſt alſo for vs. Wee then true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reſolved through a due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of theſe thinges, doe beſeech thee our moſt gracious &amp; loving Father, to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh theſe thy bleſſings in vs, &amp; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue vs in the truth of thy holie Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that as wee are according to thy
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:2309:83"/>great mercie freely adopted and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for iuſt in thy ſight by the only obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and merits, and ful ſatisfaction of Chriſt our Saviour: ſo againe that we might ſtriue, (through thine eſpecial favour,) in our daylie converſation, and in the midſt of a crooked and ſtiffnecked generation, to approue our ſelues out of the fruites of a lively faith, to be ſincere followers and embracers of thee. To which purpoſe, we begge of thee, ô Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſanctifie vs with thy Spirit, that we loathing from the heart our inborne filthines, and mortifying our members which are on earth, fornication, vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, inordinate affection, evil concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and covetouſnes which is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, &amp; putting away eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al theſe things, wrath, anger, maliciouſnes, curſed ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, filthy ſpeaking out of our mouths, and in a word, putting of the olde man with his workes: wee may, (thine onelie goodnes to vs-wardes effecting it,) bee prepared to receive the new; by putting on, as the Elect of God, tender mercy,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:2309:83"/>kindenes, humblenes of minde, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, longſuffering, forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forgiving one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finally,</hi> wee ſtirred vp with a fellow feeling of others wants, as members of one body with the reſidue of thy Saints in the Communion thereof, doe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly entreate thy diuine Maieſtie to bee gracious and louing vnto thy Church which liueth here in continuall exile &amp; warfare vpon the earth; protect it, O Lord, ſaflie vnder thy wings againſt the rage of Satan, and the furies of blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty men: particularly, for theſe of England, Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; Ireland, &amp; in them, as the Principal member ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for thine obedient ſeruant our dread Soveraigne, Lord <hi>Iames;</hi> by thy Grace King of the foreſaid Realmes &amp; Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, defender of the true, ancient, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, and Apoſtolike faith, and in all Cauſes &amp; over all Perſons within theſe his Maieſties Kingdomes next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vnder thee Supreame head &amp; gouernour: grant vnto him health and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:2309:84"/>proſperitie all his daies, crowne him ſo long as he liueth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this earth with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall victories over his enemies: giue him the ſpirit of wiſedome, knowledge, and iudgement that he may carefully &amp; vprightly go in and out before thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: enrich his Royal heart with thine heauenlie bleſſings, namely; true faith, godly zeale, loue, and feare of thy holie name euen al the daies of his life, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life once expired, crowne him in thine euerlaſting Kingdome with bliſſe and triumphant glorie.</p>
               <p>We pray thee eftwiſe for al the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Gentry, and comminalty of this Realme, and more eſpecially for the Lords of the Privie Councell, that as they are high in Honor &amp; great Peares of this Land, ſo they may be great Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers alſo in the Church to exalt and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance thy name. Bleſſe in like manner all the Cleargie and Miniſterie of this Land by what names and titles ſoeuer they are called, engraue in their breaſts that <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> that is to ſay,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:2309:84"/>an inwarde burning zeale ioined with ſoundnes of doctrine and with vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and integritie of life. Extende thy mercifull care on all Vniverſities and ſchooles the nurceries of good learning that they may (according to thy good pleaſure) remaine euermore as habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Prophets &amp; Prophets chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo long as the Sun and Moone en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth. Keepe, O Lord, &amp; direct in thy feare the Magiſtracie of this Land, that they in their Places may diſcharge a good conſcience, in the Miniſtration of equitie &amp; iuſtice, togither with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of pietie and vertue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moreover wee doe pray thee</hi> for all thoſe that ſuffer any Croſſe or trouble either ſickneſſe of body or vexation of minde, affliction, perſecution for thy names ſake and the teſtimony of a good conſcience; that it may pleaſe thee to en arme them with patience &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to perſeuere vnto the end of al their trials: knowing that patience bringeth forth experience, experience hope, and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:2309:85"/>hope maketh not aſhamed. And more particularly, we powre forth our hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſupplications and ſuites vnto thy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, for al ſuch as doe lie groueling and groaning vnder the burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſins, make thou their bed in the time of their ſicknes by putting thy Spirit into their harts, by comforting and relieuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with inward ioies, that thereby their faith may be increaſed, their hope con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, their loue enflamed, their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; perſeuerance made known vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men and Angels, tried, continued, &amp; preſerued: that neither <hi>Leviathan</hi> that crooked wylie ſerpent withall his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous aſſaults without, neither the bruiſedly afflicted conſcience within, neither the gaping gulfe of hel beneath, neither the angrie threatning heauens for our ſinnes aboue, neither the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and earthly cogitations &amp; chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of this world on the one ſide, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wicked Imps thereof on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may ſtrik a terror into our minds, but that in the aſſurance of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:2309:85"/>we may being bold &amp; confident as a Lyon, breake through them al and ſaie with the Prophet Dauid; <hi>The Lord of Hostes is with vs, the God of Iacob is our refuge</hi> And againe with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule; <hi>In all theſe things we are more then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours through him that loved vs. For I am perſwaded that neither death nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height nor depth, nor any other creature ſhalbe able to ſeparate vs, from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſt of al, we yeeld vnto thee, good Lord, moſt humble thanks for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſhowred forth, yea powred downe vpon vs out of the riches of thy Grace, that is, for our Creation in time, our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection before al time, our Preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Vocation, Iuſtification, Sanctification, and for the good hopes ſake of our Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification in the time to come: as alſo we thank thee (ſo long as we ſhal moue &amp; breath vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth) for our health,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:2309:86"/>our wealth, our food, our rayment, our education, our inſtruction, our peace &amp; tranquillitie, and for this ſo long and ſo large a time of repentaunce giuen vnto vs by the preaching of thy truth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, which vphold thou ſtil, O Lord, wee praie thee, euen for thine owne glories ſake, and for the vnſpeakeable conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſake &amp; gathering in togither of thy Saintes.</p>
               <p>That ſo in the end, we maie al meete iointlie in the vnitie of one <hi>faith,</hi> &amp; that in the meane time we may wait, for the haſtning &amp; conſummation of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt thy deare Son our Lord and Sauiour, who teſtifieth theſe things and ſaith, <hi>Surely I come quickly. Amen. Even ſo come Lord Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Tim. 2. chap. 1.2. verſes, <hi>I exhort ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that firſt of all ſupplications, praiers interceſsions, and giving of thankes bee made for all men. For Kings, and all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and a peaceable life, in all goodneſſe and honestie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:2309:86"/>
               <head>A very ſhort, but ſweete Dialogue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene an ancient deepe learned Father and his Siſter, reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon the Caſe with in themſelues.</head>
               <p>O Siſter, ſaith hee, no man is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, euery man is guilty of wicked workes, words, and thoughts: and what then ſhal we doe, when wee ſhall come before God to bee iudged. For if the righteouſneſſe of the righteous ſhal not be had in remembrance, if the iuſt ſhall ſcarſe be ſaued, where ſhall the wicked and ſinner appeare? O brother, ſhe ſaith again, this cauſeth me to wiſh with the Prophet that mine heade were a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares, that I might bewaile my ſinfull life. Indeede, ſaith the other, that is ſomewhat: for one teare in this life is better then al the <hi>weeping</hi> and <hi>gnaſhing</hi> of teeth, which ſhalbe after this life. For God is neere in this life, that is, he will be entreated to forgiue vs: but then he wilbe far of, which is, he wil not <hi>yeeld</hi> to anie petition.</p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:2309:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>As the laſt howre of thy life leaues thee: ſo the firſt howre of <hi>iudgment ſhal finde thee. For where the tree falleth, there it lieth.</hi> Eccl. 11. chap. 3. verſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:2309:87"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
